<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The defence of poesie. By Sir Phillip Sidney, Knight</title>
            <title>Defence of poetry</title>
            <author>Sidney, Philip, Sir, 1554-1586.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1595</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 121 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12225</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119205</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854412</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854412</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19832</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12225)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19832)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 904:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The defence of poesie. By Sir Phillip Sidney, Knight</title>
                  <title>Defence of poetry</title>
                  <author>Sidney, Philip, Sir, 1554-1586.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[72] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Thomas Creede] for VVilliam Ponsonby,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1595.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>The first authorized edition.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]²  B-I⁴ K² .</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19832:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19832:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19832:2"/>
            <p>THE DEFENCE OF Poeſie.</p>
            <p>By Sir Phillip Sidney, Knight.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON Printed for <hi>VVilliam Ponſonby.</hi> 1595.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:19832:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19832:3"/>
            <head>The defence of Poeſie, by <hi>Sir Philip Sidney Knight.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the right vertuous <hi>E.VV.</hi> and I, were at the Emperours Court togither, wee gaue our ſelues to learne horſemanſhip of <hi>Ion Pietro Pugliano,</hi> one that with great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation had the place of an Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire in his ſtable: and hee accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fertilnes of the Italian wit, did not onely affoord vs the demonſtration of his practiſe, but ſought to enrich our mindes with the contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons therein, which he thought moſt precious. But with none I remember mine eares were at any time more loaden, then when (either angred with ſlow paiment, or mooued with our learner like admirati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) hee exerciſed his ſpeech in the praiſe of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie. He ſaid ſouldiers were the nobleſt eſtate of mankind, and horſemen the nobleſt of ſouldiers. He ſaid they were the maiſters of warre, and ornaments of peace, ſpeedie goers, and ſtrong abiders, trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers both in Camps and Courts: nay to ſo vnblee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a point he proceeded, as that no earthly thing bred ſuch wonder to a Prince, as to be a good horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. Skill of gouernment was but a <hi>Pedanteria,</hi> in
<pb facs="tcp:19832:4"/> compariſon, then would he adde certaine praiſes by telling what a peerleſſe beaſt the horſe was, the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeruiceable Courtier without flattery, the beaſt of moſt bewtie, faithfulneſſe, courage, and ſuch more, that if I had not bene a peece of a <hi>Logician</hi> before I came to him, I thinke he would haue perſwaded me to haue wiſhed my ſelfe a horſe. But thus much at leaſt, with his no few words he draue into me, that ſelfeloue is better then any guilding, to make that ſeem gorgious wherin our ſelues be parties. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if <hi>Pulianos</hi> ſtrong affection and weake arguments will not ſatisfie you, I wil giue you a nearer example of my ſelfe, who I know not by what miſchance in theſe my not old yeares and idleſt times, hauing ſlipt into the title of a Poet, am prouoked to ſay ſomthing vnto you in the defence of that my vnelected voca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which if I handle with more good will, then good reaſons beare with me, ſince the ſcholler is to be pardoned that followeth the ſteps of his maiſter. And yet I muſt ſay, that as I haue more iuſt cauſe to make a pittifull defence of poore Poetrie, which from almoſt the higheſt eſtimation of learning, is falne to be the laughing ſtocke of children, ſo haue I need to bring ſome more auaileable proofes, ſince the former is by no man bard of his deſerued credit, the ſilly later, hath had euen the names of <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> vſed to the defacing of it, with great daunger of ciuill warre among the Muſes. And firſt truly to all them that profeſsing learning enuey againſt Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, may iuſtly be obiected, that they go very neare to vngratefulneſſe, to ſeeke to deface that which in the nobleſt nations and languages that are knowne,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:4"/> hath bene the firſt light giuer to ignorance, and firſt nurſe whoſe milke litle &amp; litle enabled them to feed afterwards of tougher knowledges. And will you play the Hedge-hogge, that being receiued into the den, draue out his hoſt? Or rather the Vipers, that with their birth kill their parents? Let learned <hi>Greece</hi> in any of his manifold Sciences, be able to ſhew me one booke before <hi>Muſaeus, Homer,</hi> &amp; <hi>Heſiod,</hi> all three nothing elſe but Poets. Nay let any Hiſtorie bee brought, that can ſay any writers were there before them, if they were not men of the ſame skill, as <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus, Linus,</hi> and ſome other are named, who hauing bene the firſt of that country that made pennes deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerers of their knowledge to the poſteritie, nay iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly challenge to bee called their Fathers in learning. For not onely in time they had this prioritie, (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in it ſelfe antiquitie be venerable) but went before them, as cauſes to draw with their charming ſweetneſſe the wild vntamed wits to an admiration of knowledge. So as <hi>Amphion,</hi> was ſaid to mooue ſtones with his Poetry, to build <hi>Thebes,</hi> and <hi>Orpheus</hi> to be liſtned to by beaſts, indeed ſtonie and beaſtly people. So among the <hi>Romans,</hi> were <hi>Liuius, Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicus,</hi> and <hi>Ennius,</hi> ſo in the Italian language, the firſt that made it aſpire to be a treaſure-houſe of Science, were the Poets <hi>Dante, Bocace,</hi> and <hi>Petrach.</hi> So in our Engliſh, wer <hi>Gower,</hi> and <hi>Chawcer,</hi> after whom, enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged &amp; delighted with their excellent foregoing, others haue folowed to bewtify our mother toong, aſwel in the ſame kind as other arts. This did ſo nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſhew it ſelf, <hi>y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> of <hi>Greece</hi> durſt not a lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g time apear to <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> world, but vnder <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> mask of poets.
<pb facs="tcp:19832:5"/> So <hi>Thales, Empedocles,</hi> and <hi>Parmenides,</hi> ſang their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Philoſophie in verſes. So did <hi>Pithagoras</hi> and <hi>Phocillides,</hi> their morall Councels. So did <hi>Tirteus</hi> in warre matters, and <hi>Solon</hi> in matters of pollicie, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they being Poets, did exerciſe their delightfull vaine in thoſe points of higheſt knowledge, which before them laie hidden to the world. For, that wiſe <hi>Solon</hi> was directly a Poet, it is manifeſt, hauing writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in verſe the notable Fable of the <hi>Atlantick</hi> Iland, which was continued by <hi>Plato.</hi> And truly euen <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> who ſo euer well conſidereth, ſhall finde that in the body of his worke though the inſide &amp; ſtrength were Philoſophie, the skin as it were and beautie, depended moſt of Poetrie. For all ſtands vpon Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logues, wherein hee faines many honeſt Burgeſſes of <hi>Athens</hi> ſpeak of ſuch matters, that if they had bene ſet on the Racke, they would neuer haue confeſſed them: beſides his Poeticall deſcribing the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of their meetings, as the well ordering of a banquet, the delicacie of a walke, with enterlacing meere Tales, as <hi>Gyges Ring</hi> and others, which, who knowes not to bee flowers of Poetrie, did neuer walke into <hi>Appollos</hi> Garden. And euen <hi>Hiſtoriogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> although their lippes ſound of things done, and veritie be written in their foreheads, haue bene glad to borrow both faſhion and perchance weight of the Poets. So <hi>Herodotus</hi> entituled his Hiſtorie, by the name of the nine Muſes, and both he and all the reſt that followed him, either ſtale, or vſurped of Poetrie, their paſsionate deſcribing of paſsions, the many particularities of battels which no man could affirme, or if that be denied me, long Orations put
<pb facs="tcp:19832:5"/> in the mouthes of great Kings and Captains, which it is certaine they neuer pronounced. So that truly neither <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> nor <hi>Historiographer,</hi> could at the firſt haue entered into the gates of populer iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, if they had not taken a great paſport of Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, which in all nations at this day where learning flouriſheth not, is plaine to be ſeene: in all which, they haue ſome feeling of Poetry. In <hi>Turkey,</hi> beſides their law giuing Diuines, they haue no other wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters but Poets. In our neighbour Countrey <hi>Ireland,</hi> where truly learning goes verie bare, yet are their Poets held in a deuout reuerence. Euen among the moſt barbarous and ſimple <hi>Indians,</hi> where no wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting is, yet haue they their Poets who make &amp; ſing ſongs which they call <hi>Arentos,</hi> both of their Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors deeds, and praiſes of their Gods. A ſufficient probability, that if euer learning come among them, it muſt be by hauing their hard dull wittes ſoftened and ſharpened with the ſweete delights of Poetrie, for vntill they finde a pleaſure in the exerciſe of the minde, great promiſes of much knowledge, wil lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle perſuade them that know not the frutes of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. In <hi>VVales,</hi> the true remnant of the auncient <hi>Brittons,</hi> as there are good authorities to ſhew, the long time they had Poets which they called <hi>Bardes:</hi> ſo thorow all the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>queſts of <hi>Romans, Saxons, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Normans,</hi> ſome of whom, did ſeeke to ruine all memory of learning from among them, yet do their Poets euen to this day laſt: ſo as it is not more nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſoone beginning, then in long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. But ſince the Authors of moſt of our Sciences, were the <hi>Romanes,</hi> and before them the <hi>Greekes,</hi> let vs
<pb facs="tcp:19832:6"/> a litle ſtand vpon their authorities, but euen ſo farre as to ſee what names they haue giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto this now ſcorned skill. Among the <hi>Romanes</hi> a Poet was called <hi>Vares,</hi> which is as much as a diuiner, foreſeer, or Prophet, as by his conioyned words <hi>Vaticinium,</hi> and <hi>Vaticinari,</hi> is manifeſt, ſo heauenly a title did that excellent people beſtowe vppon this hart-ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſhing knowledge, and ſo farre were they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried into the admiration thereof, that they though<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the chanceable hitting vppon any of ſuch ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, great foretokens of their following fortunes, were placed. Whereupon grew the word of <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Vergilianae,</hi> when by ſuddaine opening <hi>Virgils</hi> booke, they lighted vppon ſome verſe of his, as it is reported by many, whereof the Hiſtories of the <hi>Emperours</hi> liues are full. As of <hi>Albinus</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour of our Iland, who in his childhood met with this verſe <hi>Arma amens capio, nec ſat rationis in armis:</hi> and in his age performed it, although it were a verie vaine and godleſſe ſuperſtition, as alſo it was, to thinke ſpirits were commaunded by ſuch verſes, whereupon this word <hi>Charmes</hi> deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of <hi>Carmina,</hi> commeth: ſo yet ſerueth it to ſhew the great reuerence thoſe wittes were held in, and altogither not without ground, ſince both by the Oracles of <hi>Delphos</hi> and <hi>Sybillas</hi> propheſies, were wholly deliuered in verſes, for that ſame exquiſite obſeruing of number and meaſure in the words, and that high flying libertie of conceit propper to the Poet, did ſeeme to haue ſome diuine force in it. And may not I preſume a little farther, to ſhewe the reaſonableneſſe of this word <hi>Vatis,</hi> and ſay that the
<pb facs="tcp:19832:6"/> holy <hi>Dauids</hi> Pſalms are a diuine <hi>Poeme?</hi> If I do, I ſhal not do it without the teſtimony of great learned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both auncient and moderne. But euen the name of Pſalmes wil ſpeak for me, which being interpreted, is nothing but Songs: then that it is fully written in meeter as all learned <hi>Hebritians</hi> agree, although the rules be not yet fully found. Laſtly and principally, his handling his prophecie, which is meerly Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. For what elſe is the awaking his muſical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, the often and free chaunging of perſons, his notable <hi>Proſopopeias,</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he maketh you as it were ſee God comming in his maieſtie, his telling of the beaſts ioyfulneſſe, and hils leaping, but a heauenly poeſie, wherin almoſt he ſheweth himſelfe a paſsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate louer of that vnſpeakable and euerlaſting bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, to be ſeene by the eyes of the mind, onely cleared by faith? But truly now hauing named him, I feare I ſeeme to prophane that holy name, applying it to Poetry, which is among vs throwne downe to ſo ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous an eſtimation. But they that with quiet iudgements wil looke a litle deeper into it, ſhal find the end &amp; working of it ſuch, as being rightly appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, deſerueth not to be ſcourged out of the Church of God. But now let vs ſee how the Greekes haue named it, and how they deemed of it. The Greekes named him <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which name, hath as the moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent, gone through other languages, it commeth of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which is to make: wherin I know not whether by luck or wiſedome, we Engliſhmen haue met with the Greekes in calling him a Maker. Which name, how high and incomparable a title it is, I had rather were knowne by marking the ſcope
<pb facs="tcp:19832:7"/> of other ſciences, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any partial allegatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. There is no Art deliuered vnto mankind that hath not the workes of nature for his principall obiect, without which they could not conſiſt, and on which they ſo depend, as they become Actors &amp; Plaiers, as it were of what nature will haue ſet forth. So doth the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stronomer</hi> looke vpon the ſtarres, and by that he ſeeth ſet downe what order nature hath taken therein. So doth the <hi>Geometritian</hi> &amp; <hi>Arithmititian,</hi> in their diuers ſorts of quantities. So doth the <hi>Muſitians</hi> in times tel you, which by nature agree, which not. The natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Philoſopher</hi> thereon hath his name, and the (mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſtandeth vppon the naturall vertues, vices, or paſsions of man: and follow nature ſaith he therein, and thou ſhalt not erre. The <hi>Lawier</hi> ſaith, what men haue determined. The <hi>Historian,</hi> what men haue done. The <hi>Gramarian,</hi> ſpeaketh onely of the rules of ſpeech, and the <hi>Rhetoritian</hi> and <hi>Logiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> conſidering what in nature wil ſooneſt prooue, and perſwade thereon, giue artificiall rules, which ſtill are compaſſed within the circle of a queſtion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the propoſed matter. The <hi>Phiſitian</hi> way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the nature of mans bodie, &amp; the nature of things helpfull, or hurtfull vnto it. And the <hi>Metaphiſicke</hi> though it be in the ſecond &amp; abſtract Notions, and therefore be counted ſupernaturall, yet doth hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed build vpon the depth of nature. Only the Poet diſdeining to be tied to any ſuch ſubiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, lifted vp with the vigor of his own inuention, doth grow in effect into an other nature: in making things either better then nature bringeth foorth, or quite a new, formes ſuch as neuer were in nature: as the <hi>Heroes,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:7"/> Demigods, Cyclops, Chymeras, Furies,</hi> and ſuch like; ſo as he goeth hand in hand with nature, not encloſed within the narrow warrant of her gifts, but freely raunging within the Zodiack of his owne wit. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture neuer ſet foorth the earth in ſo rich Tapiſtry as diuerſe Poets haue done, neither with ſo pleaſaunt riuers, fruitfull trees, ſweete ſmelling flowers, nor whatſoeuer els may make the too much loued earth more lonely: her world is braſen, the Poets only de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer a golden. But let thoſe things alone and goe to man, for whom as the other things are, ſo it ſeemeth in him her vttermoſt comming is imploied: &amp; know whether ſhe haue brought foorth ſo true a louer as <hi>Theagenes,</hi> ſo conſtant a friend as <hi>Pylades,</hi> ſo valiant a man as <hi>Orlando,</hi> ſo right a Prince as <hi>Xenophons Cyrus,</hi> ſo excellent a man euery way as <hi>Virgils Aeneas.</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let this be ieſtingly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued, bicauſe the works of the one be eſſenciall, the other in imitation or fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: for euerie vnderſtanding, knoweth the skill of ech Artificer ſtandeth in that <hi>Idea,</hi> or fore conceit of the worke, and not in the worke it ſelfe. And that the Poet hath that <hi>Idea,</hi> is manifeſt, by deliuering them foorth in ſuch excellencie as he had imagined them: which deliuering foorth, alſo is not wholly imaginatiue, as we are wont to ſay by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that build Caſtles in the aire: but ſo farre ſubſtancially it wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, not onely to make a <hi>Cyrus,</hi> which had bene but a particular excellency as nature might haue done, but to beſtow a <hi>Cyrus</hi> vpon the world to make ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Cyruſſes,</hi> if they will learne aright, why and how that maker made him. Neither let it be deemed too ſawcy a compariſon, to ballance the higheſt point of
<pb facs="tcp:19832:8"/> mans wit, with the efficacie of nature: but rather giue right honor to the heauenly maker of that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, who hauing made man to his owne likenes, ſet him beyond and ouer all the workes of that ſecond nature, which in nothing he ſheweth ſo much as in Poetry; when with the force of a diuine breath, he bringeth things foorth ſurpaſsing her doings: with no ſmall arguments to the incredulous of that firſt accurſed fall of <hi>Adam,</hi> ſince our erected wit maketh vs know what perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is, and yet our infected wil keepeth vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reaching vnto it. But theſe argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts will by few be vnderſtood, and by fewer graunted: thus much I hope wil be giuen me, that the Greeks with ſome probability of reaſon, gaue him the name aboue all names of learning. Now let vs goe to a more ordinarie opening of him, that the truth may be the more palpable: and ſo I hope though we get not ſo vnmatched a praiſe as the <hi>Etimologie</hi> of his names will graunt, yet his verie deſcription which no man will denie, ſhall not iuſtly be barred from a principall commendation. <hi>Poeſie</hi> therefore, is an Art of <hi>Imitation:</hi> for ſo <hi>Aristotle</hi> termeth it in the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, a repreſenting, counterfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or figuring forth to ſpeake Metaphorically. A ſpeaking <hi>Picture,</hi> with this end to teach and delight. Of this haue bene three generall kindes, the chiefe both in antiquitie and excellencie, were they that did imitate the vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiueable excellencies of God. Such were <hi>Dauid</hi> in his Pſalmes, <hi>Salomon</hi> in his ſong of ſongs, in his <hi>Eccleſiaſtes</hi> and <hi>Prouerbes. Moſes</hi> and <hi>Debora,</hi> in their Hymnes, and the wryter of <hi>Iobe:</hi> Which beſide other, the learned <hi>Emanuell,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:8"/> Tremelius,</hi> and <hi>F. Iunius,</hi> doo entitle the Poeticall part of the ſcripture: againſt theſe none will ſpeake that hath the holie Ghoſt in due holie reuerence. In this kinde, though in a full wrong diuinitie, were <hi>Orpheus, Amphion, Homer</hi> in his himnes, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other both <hi>Greeke</hi> and <hi>Romanes.</hi> And this <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie</hi> muſt be vſed by whoſoeuer will follow <hi>S. Paules</hi> counſaile, in ſinging Pſalmes when they are mery, and I knowe is vſed with the frute of comfort by ſome, when in ſorrowfull panges of their death bringing ſinnes, they finde the conſolation of the neuer leauing goodnes. The ſecond kinde, is of them that deale with matters Philoſophicall, either morall as <hi>Tirteus, Phocilides, Cato;</hi> or naturall, as <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretius,</hi> and <hi>Virgils Georgikes;</hi> or Aſtronomicall as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nilius</hi> and <hi>Pontanus;</hi> or Hiſtoricall as <hi>Lucan:</hi> which who miſlike the fault, is in their iudgement quite out of taſt, &amp; not in the ſweet food of ſweetly vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red knowledge. But bicauſe this ſecond ſort is wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped within the folde of the propoſed ſubiect, and takes not the free courſe of his own inuentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they properly bee Poets or no, let <hi>Gramarians</hi> diſpute; and goe to the third indeed right Poets, of whom chiefly this queſtion ariſeth: betwixt whom and theſe ſecond, is ſuch a kinde of difference, as betwixt the meaner ſort of Painters, who coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyt onely ſuch faces as are ſet before them, and the more excelent, who hauing no law but wit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow that in colours vpon you, which is fitteſt for the eye to ſee, as the conſtant, though lamenting looke of <hi>Lucretia,</hi> when ſhee puniſhed in her ſelfe anothers faulte: wherein hee painteth not
<pb facs="tcp:19832:9"/> 
               <hi>Lucretia</hi> whom he neuer ſaw, but painteth the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bewty of ſuch a vertue. For theſe third be they which moſt properly do imitate to teach &amp; delight: and to imitate, borrow nothing of what is, hath bin, or ſhall be, but range onely reined with learned diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, into the diuine conſideration of what may be and ſhould be. Theſe be they that as the firſt and moſt noble ſort, may iuſtly be termed <hi>Vates:</hi> ſo theſe are waited on in the excellenteſt languages and beſt vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dings, with the fore deſcribed name of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets. For theſe indeed do meerly make to imitate, and imitate both to delight &amp; teach, and delight to moue men to take that goodneſſe in hand, which without delight they would flie as from a ſtranger; and teach to make them know that goodneſſe wherunto they are moued: which being the nobleſt ſcope to which euer any learning was directed, yet want there not idle tongues to barke at them. Theſe be ſubdiuided into ſundry more ſpeciall denominations. The moſt notable be the <hi>Heroick, Lyrick, Tragick, Comick, Saty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick, Iambick, Elegiack, Pastorall,</hi> and certaine others: ſome of theſe being tearmed according to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they deale with, ſome by the ſort of verſe they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked beſt to write in, for indeed the greateſt part of Poets, haue apparelled their poeticall inuentions, in that numbrous kind of writing which is called <hi>verſ.</hi> Indeed but apparelled verſe: being but an ornament and no cauſe to Poetrie, ſince there haue bene many moſt excellent Poets that neuer verſefied, and now ſwarme many verſefiers that need neuer anſwere to the name of Poets. For <hi>Xenophon</hi> who did imitate ſo excellently as to giue vs <hi>effigiem iusti imperii,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:19832:9"/> pourtraiture of a iuſt Empyre vnder the name of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith of him, made therein an abſolute heroicall Poeme. So did <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> in his ſugred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention of that picture of loue in <hi>Theagenes</hi> &amp; <hi>Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riclea,</hi> and yet both theſe wrote in proſe, which I ſpeake to ſhew, that it is not ryming and verſing that maketh a Poet, (no more then a long gown maketh an Aduocate, who though he pleaded in Armour, ſhould be an Aduocat and no ſouldier) but it is that faining notable images of vertues, vices, or what els, with that delightfull teaching, which muſt be the right deſcribing note to know a Poet by. Although indeed the Senate of Poets hath choſen verſe as their fitteſt raiment: meaning as in matter, they paſſed all in all, ſo in maner, to go beyond them: not ſpeaking table talke faſhion, or like men in a dreame, words as they chanceably fall from the mouth, but peaſing each ſillable of eache word by iuſt proportion, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the dignitie of the ſubiect. Now therfore it ſhal not be amiſſe, firſt to way this latter ſort of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etrie by his workes, and then by his parts, and if in neither of theſe Anatomies hee be condemnable, I hope we ſhall obteine a more fauourable ſentence. This purifying of wit, this enriching of memorie, enabling of iudgement, and enlarging of conceit, which commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly we cal learning, vnder what name ſo euer it come forth, or to what immediate end ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it be directed, the finall end is, to lead and draw vs to as high a perfection, as our degenerate ſoules made worſe by their clay-lodgings, can be capable of. This according to the inclination of man, bred many formed impreſsions. For ſome that thought
<pb facs="tcp:19832:10"/> this felicity principally to be gotten by knowledge, and no knowledge to be ſo high or heauenly, as ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance with the ſtars; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomie:</hi> others perſwading the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to be <hi>Demygods,</hi> if they knew the cauſes of things, became naturall and ſupernaturall <hi>Philoſophers.</hi> Some an admirable delight drew to <hi>Muſicke;</hi> and ſome the certaintie of demonſtration to the <hi>Mathematicks:</hi> but all one and other hauing this ſcope to know, &amp; by knowledge to lift vp the minde from the dungeon of the bodie, to the enioying his owne diuine eſſence. But when by the ballance of experience it was found, that the <hi>Astronomer</hi> looking to the ſtars might fall in a ditch, that the inquiring <hi>Philoſopher</hi> might be blind in him ſelf, &amp; the <hi>Mathematician,</hi> might draw forth a ſtraight line with a crooked hart. Then lo did proofe, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerruler of opinions make manifeſt, that all theſe are but ſeruing ſciences; which as they haue a priuate end in themſelues, ſo yet are they all directed to the higheſt end of the miſtreſſe knowledge by <hi>y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
               </hi> Greeks <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſtands as I thinke, in the knowledge of a mans ſelfe, in the Ethike and Politique conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, with the end of well doing, and not of well knowing onely. Euen as the Sadlers next ende is to make a good Saddle, but his further ende, to ſerue a nobler facultie, which is horſmanſhip, ſo the horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans to ſouldiery: and the ſouldier not only to haue the skill, but to performe the practiſe of a ſouldier. So that the ending end of all earthly learning, being verteous action, thoſe skils that moſt ſerue to bring forth that, haue a moſt iuſt title to be Princes ouer al the reſt: wherin if we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhew, the Poet is worthy to
<pb facs="tcp:19832:10"/> haue it before any other competitors: among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> principally to challenge it, ſtep forth the moral <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers,</hi> whom me thinkes I ſee comming towards me, with a ſullain grauitie, as though they could not abide vice by day-light, rudely cloathed, for to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe outwardly their contempt of outward things, with bookes in their hands againſt glorie, whereto they ſet their names: ſophiſtically ſpeaking againſt ſubtiltie, and angry with any man in whom they ſee the foule fault of anger. Theſe men caſting larges as they go of definitions, diuitions, and diſtinctions, with a ſcornful interrogatiue, do ſoberly aske, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be poſsible to find any path ſo ready to lead a man to vertue, as that which teacheth what vertue is, &amp; teacheth it not only by deliuering forth his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry being, his cauſes and effects, but alſo by making knowne his enemie vice, which muſt be deſtroyed, and his comberſome ſeruant paſsion, which muſt be maſtred: by ſhewing the generalities that contains it, and the ſpecialities that are deriued from it. Laſtly by plaine ſetting downe, how it extends it ſelfe out of the limits of a mans owne little world, to the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of families, and mainteining of publike ſocieties. The <hi>Historian</hi> ſcarſely giues leiſure to the <hi>Moralist</hi> to ſay ſo much, but that he loaden with old Mouſe-eaten Records, authoriſing himſelfe for the moſt part vpon other Hiſtories, whoſe greateſt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities are built vppon the notable foundation <hi>Hereſay,</hi> hauing much ado to accord differing wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, &amp; to pick truth out of partiality: better acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a 1000. yeres ago, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the preſent age, and yet better knowing how this world goes, then
<pb facs="tcp:19832:11"/> how his owne wit runnes, curious for Antiquities, and inquiſitiue of Nouelties, a wonder to yoong folkes, and a Tyrant in table talke; denieth in a great chafe, that any man for teaching of vertue, and ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues actions, is comparable to him. I am <hi>Testis tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porum, lux veritatis, vita memoriae, magistra vitae, nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cia vetustatis.</hi> The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaith he, teacheth a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putatiue vertue, but I do an actiue. His vertue is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in the dangerleſſe <hi>Academy</hi> of <hi>Plato:</hi> but mine ſheweth forth her honourable face in the battailes of <hi>Marathon, Pharſalia, Poietiers,</hi> and <hi>Agincourt.</hi> Hee teacheth vertue by certaine abſtract conſiderations: but I onely bid you follow the footing of them that haue gone before you. Old aged experience, goeth beyond the fine witted <hi>Philoſopher:</hi> but I giue the experience of many ages. Laſtly, if he make the ſong Booke, I put the learners hand to the Lute, and if he be the guide, I am the light. Then would he alleage you innumerable examples, confirming ſtorie by ſtories, how much the wiſeſt Senators and Princes, haue bene directed by the credit of Hiſtorie, as <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Alphonſus</hi> of <hi>Aragon,</hi> (and who not if need be.) At length, the long line of their diſputation makes a point in this, that the one giueth the precept, &amp; the other the example. Now whom ſhall we find, ſince the queſtion ſtandeth for the higheſt forme in the ſchoole of learning to be moderator? Truly as mee ſeemeth, the Poet, and if not a moderator, euen the man that ought to carry the title from them both: &amp; much more from all other ſeruing ſciences. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore compare we the <hi>Poet</hi> with the <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> &amp; with the morall <hi>Philoſopher:</hi> and if hee goe beyond them
<pb facs="tcp:19832:11"/> both, no other humaine skill can match him. For as for the diuine, with all reuerence it is euer to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, not onely for hauing his ſcope as far beyond any of theſe, as Eternitie exceedeth a moment: but euen for paſsing ech of theſe in themſelues. And for the <hi>Lawier,</hi> though <hi>Ius</hi> be the daughter of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> the chiefe of vertues, yet becauſe he ſeeks to make men good, rather <hi>formidine panae,</hi> then <hi>virtutis amore:</hi> or to ſay righter, doth not endeuor to make men good, but that their euill hurt not others, hauing no care ſo he be a good citizen, how bad a man he be. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as our wickednes maketh him neceſſarie, and neceſsitie maketh him honorable, ſo is he not in the deepeſt truth to ſtand in ranck with theſe, who al en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuour to take naughtineſſe away, and plant good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe euen in the ſecreteſt cabinet of our ſoules: and theſe foure are all that any way deale in the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of mens manners, which being the ſupreme knowledge, they that beſt breed it, deſerue the beſt commendation. The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> therefore, and the <hi>Historian,</hi> are they which would win the goale, the one by precept, the other by example: but both, not hauing both, doo both halt. For the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe with thornie arguments, the bare rule, is ſo hard of vtterance, and ſo miſtie to be conceiued, that one that hath no other guide but him, ſhall wade in him till he be old, before he ſhall finde ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe to be honeſt. For his knowledge ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſo vpon the abſtract and generall, that happie is that man who may vnderſtand him, and more hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, that can apply what he doth vnderſtand. On the other ſide, the <hi>Historian</hi> wanting the precept, is ſo
<pb facs="tcp:19832:12"/> tied, not to what ſhould be, but to what is, to the particular truth of things, and not to the general rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of things, that his example draweth no neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie conſequence, and therefore a leſſe fruitfull doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine. Now doth the peerleſſe Poet performe both, for whatſoeuer the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſaith ſhould be done, he giues a perfect picture of it by ſome one, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he preſuppoſeth it was done, ſo as he coupleth the generall notion with the particuler example. A per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect picture I ſay, for hee yeeldeth to the powers of the minde an image of that whereof the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> beſtoweth but a wordiſh deſcription, which doth neither ſtrike, pearce, nor poſſeſſe, the ſight of the ſoule ſo much, as that other doth. For as in outward things to a man that had neuer ſeene an <hi>Elephant,</hi> or a <hi>Rinoceros,</hi> who ſhould tell him moſt exquiſitely all their ſhape, cullour, bigneſſe, and particuler marks, or of a gorgious pallace an <hi>Architecture,</hi> who decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the full bewties, might well make the hearer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to repeat as it were by roat all he had heard, yet ſhould neuer ſatiſfie his inward conceit, with being witneſſe to it ſelfe of a true liuely knowledge: but the ſame ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, aſſoon as he might ſee thoſe beaſts wel painted, or that houſe wel in modell, ſhuld ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies grow without need of any deſcription to a iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial comprehending of them, ſo no doubt the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher</hi> with his learned definitions, be it of vertues or vices, matters of publike policy or priuat gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, repleniſheth the memorie with many infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble grounds of wiſdom, which notwithſtanding lie darke before the imaginatiue and iudging power, if they be not illuminated or figured forth by the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb facs="tcp:19832:12"/> picture of <hi>Poeſie. Tully</hi> taketh much paines, and many times not without Poeticall helpes to make vs know the force, loue of our country hath in vs. Let vs but heare old <hi>Anchices,</hi> ſpeaking in the middeſt of <hi>Troies</hi> flames, or ſee <hi>Vliſſes</hi> in the fulneſſe of all <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lipſoes</hi> delightes, bewaile his abſence from barraine and beggerly <hi>Ithecae.</hi> Anger the <hi>Stoickes</hi> ſaid, was a ſhort madneſſe: let but <hi>Sophocles</hi> bring you <hi>Aiax</hi> on a ſtage, killing or whipping ſheepe and oxen, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them the Army of Greekes, with their Chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines <hi>Agamemnon,</hi> and <hi>Menelaus:</hi> and tell me if you haue not a more familiar inſight into Anger, then finding in the ſchoolemen his <hi>Genus</hi> and <hi>Difference.</hi> See whether wiſdom and temperance in <hi>Vliſſes</hi> and <hi>Diomedes,</hi> valure in <hi>Achilles,</hi> friendſhip in <hi>Niſus</hi> and <hi>Eurialus,</hi> euen to an ignorant man carry not an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parant ſhining: and contrarily, the remorſe of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in <hi>Oedipus;</hi> the ſoone repenting pride in <hi>Aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memnon;</hi> the ſelfe deuouring crueltie in his father <hi>Atreus;</hi> the violence of ambition in the two <hi>Theban</hi> brothers; the ſower ſweetneſſe of reuenge in <hi>Medea;</hi> and to fall lower, the <hi>Terentian Gnato,</hi> and our <hi>Chaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Pander</hi> ſo expreſt, that we now vſe their names, to ſignifie their Trades: And finally, all vertues, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and paſsions, ſo in their owne naturall ſtates, laide to the view, that we ſeeme not to heare of them, but clearly to ſee through them. But e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in the moſt excellent determination of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, what <hi>Philoſophers</hi> counſaile can ſo readely direct a Prince, as the feined <hi>Cirus</hi> in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> or a vertuous man in all fortunes: as <hi>Aeneas</hi> in <hi>Virgill,</hi> or a whole Common-wealth, as the Way
<pb facs="tcp:19832:13"/> of Sir Thomas Moores <hi>Eutopia.</hi> I ſay the Way, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe where Sir Thomas Moore erred, it was the fault of the man and not of the Poet: for that Way of patterning a Common-wealth, was moſt abſolute though hee perchaunce hath not ſo abſolutely performed it. For the queſtion is, whether the fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Image of Poetrie, or the reguler inſtruction of Philoſophie, hath the more force in teaching? Wherein if the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> haue more rightly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelues <hi>Philoſophers</hi> then the <hi>Poets,</hi> haue attei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the high toppe of their profeſsion (as in truth <hi>Mediocribus eſſe poetis non Dii, non homines, non conceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re columnae,</hi>) it is (I ſay againe) not the fault of the Art, but that by fewe men that Art can be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. Certainly euen our Sauiour Chriſt could as well haue giuen the morall common places of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſſe and humbleneſſe, as the diuine nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>Diues</hi> and <hi>Lazarus,</hi> or of diſobedience and mercy, as that heauenly diſcourſe of the loſt childe and the gracious Father, but that his through ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching wiſedome, knew the eſtate of <hi>Diues</hi> burning in hell, and of <hi>Lazarus</hi> in <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, would more conſtantly as it were, inhabit both the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie and iudgement. Truly for my ſelfe (mee ſeemes) I ſee before mine eyes, the loſt childs diſdainful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digalitie, turned to enuy a Swines dinner: which by the learned <hi>Diuines</hi> are thought not Hiſtorical acts, but inſtructing Parables. For concluſion, I ſay the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> teacheth, but he teacheth obſcurely, ſo as the learned onely can vnderſtand him, that is to ſay, he teacheth them that are alreadie taught. But the Poet is the food for the tendreſt ſtomacks, the Poet
<pb facs="tcp:19832:13"/> is indeed, the right populer <hi>Philoſopher.</hi> Whereof <hi>Eſops</hi> Tales giue good proofe, whoſe prettie Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gories ſtealing vnder the formall Tales of beaſtes, makes many more beaſtly then beaſts: begin to hear the ſound of vertue from thoſe dumbe ſpeakers. But now may it be alleadged, that if this imagining of matters be ſo fit for the imagination, then muſt the <hi>Historian</hi> needs ſurpaſſe, who brings you images of true matters, ſuch as indeed were done, and not ſuch as fantaſtically or falſly may be ſuggeſted to haue bin done. Truly <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> himſelfe in his diſcourſe of <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie,</hi> plainly determineth this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſaying; that <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, it is more Philoſophicall and more then Hiſtory. His reaſon is, becauſe <hi>Poeſie</hi> dealeth with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is to ſay, with the vniuerſall conſideration, and the Hiſtorie with <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the particular. Now ſaith he, the vniuerſall wayes what is fit to be ſaid or done, either in likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood or neceſsitie, which the <hi>Poeſie</hi> conſidereth in his impoſed names: and the particular onely mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth whether <hi>Alcibiades</hi> did or ſuffered this or that. Thus farre <hi>Aristotle.</hi> Which reaſon of his, as all his is moſt full of reaſon. For indeed if the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were, whether it were better to haue a particular act truly or falſly ſet downe, there is no doubt which is to be choſen, no more then whether you had rather haue <hi>Veſpacians</hi> Picture right as he was, or at the Painters pleaſure nothing reſembling. But if the queſtion be for your owne vſe and learning, whether it be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to haue it ſet downe as it ſhould be, or as it was; then certainly is more doctrinable, the fained <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> then the true <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Iustin:</hi> and the
<pb facs="tcp:19832:14"/> fained <hi>Aeneas</hi> in <hi>Virgill,</hi> then the right <hi>Aeneas</hi> in <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Phrigius:</hi> as to a Ladie that deſired to faſhion her countenance to the beſt grace: a Painter ſhuld more benefite her to pourtrait a moſt ſweete face, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Canidia</hi> vppon it, then to paint <hi>Canidia</hi> as ſhee was, who <hi>Horace</hi> ſweareth was full ill fauoured. If the <hi>Poet</hi> do his part aright, he wil ſhew you in <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talus Atreus,</hi> and ſuch like, nothing that is not to be ſhunned; in <hi>Cyrus, Aeneas, Vliſſes,</hi> each thing to be followed: where the <hi>Historian</hi> bound to tell things as things were, cannot be liberall, without hee will be Poeticall of a perfect patterne, but as in <hi>Alexander</hi> or <hi>Scipio</hi> himſelfe, ſhew doings, ſome to be liked, ſome to be miſliked; and then how wil you diſcerne what to follow, but by your own diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which you had without reading <hi>Q. Curtius.</hi> And whereas a man may ſay, though in vniuerſall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of doctrine, the <hi>Poet</hi> preuaileth, yet that the Hiſtorie in his ſaying ſuch a thing was done, doth warrant a man more in that he ſhall follow. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is manifeſt, that if he ſtand vpon that was, as if he ſhould argue, becauſe it rained yeſterday, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſhould raine to day, then indeede hath it ſome aduantage to a groſſe conceit. But if hee knowe an example onely enformes a coniectured likelihood, and ſo goe by reaſon, the <hi>Poet</hi> doth ſo farre exceed him, as hee is to frame his example to that which is moſt reaſonable, be it in warlike, politike, or priuate matters, where the <hi>Historian</hi> in his bare, was, hath many times that which we call fortune, to ouerrule the beſt wiſedome. Manie times he muſt tell euents, whereof he can yeeld no
<pb facs="tcp:19832:14"/> cauſe, or if he do, it muſt be poetically. For that a fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned example hath as much force to teach, as a true example (for as for to mooue, it is cleare, ſince the fained may be tuned to the higheſt key of paſsion) let vs take one example wherein an <hi>Historian</hi> and a <hi>Poet</hi> did concurre. <hi>Herodotus</hi> and <hi>Iustin</hi> doth both teſtifie, that <hi>Zopirus,</hi> King <hi>Darius</hi> faithfull ſeruant, ſeeing his maiſter long reſiſted by the rebellious <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonians,</hi> fained himſelfe in extreame diſgrace of his King, for verifying of which, he cauſed his owne noſe and eares to be cut off, and ſo flying to the <hi>Babylonians</hi> was receiued, and for his knowne va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lure ſo farre creadited, that hee did finde meanes to deliuer them ouer to <hi>Darius.</hi> Much like mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter doth <hi>Liuy</hi> record of <hi>Tarquinius,</hi> and his ſonne. <hi>Xenophon</hi> excellently faineth ſuch an other Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geme, performed by <hi>Abradates</hi> in <hi>Cyrus</hi> behalfe. Now would I faine knowe, if occaſion be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto you, to ſerue your Prince by ſuch an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt diſsimulation, why you do not as well learne it of <hi>Xenophons</hi> fiction, as of the others veritie: and truly ſo much the better, as you ſhall ſaue your noſe by the bargaine. For <hi>Abradates</hi> did not coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeyt ſo farre. So then the beſt of the <hi>Historian</hi> is ſubiect to the <hi>Poet,</hi> for whatſoeuer action or faction, whatſoeuer counſaile, pollicie, or warre, ſtratageme, the <hi>Historian</hi> is bounde to recite, that may the <hi>Poet</hi> if hee lift with his imitation make his owne; bewtifying it both for further teaching, and more delighting as it pleaſe him: hauing all fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dante</hi> his heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his hell, vnder the authority of his pen. Which if I be asked what <hi>Poets</hi> haue don ſo?
<pb facs="tcp:19832:15"/> as I might wel name ſome, ſo yet ſay I, and ſay again, I ſpeake of the Art and not of the Artificer. Now to that which commonly is attributed to the praiſe of Hiſtorie, in reſpect of the notable learning, is got by marking the ſucceſſe, as though therein a man ſhuld ſee vertue exalted, &amp; vice puniſhed: truly that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation is peculier to Poetrie, and farre off from Hiſtorie; for indeed Poetrie euer ſets vertue ſo out in her beſt cullours, making fortune her well-way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting handmayd, that one muſt needs be enamoured of her. Well may you ſee <hi>Vliſſes</hi> in a ſtorme and in other hard plights, but they are but exerciſes of pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience &amp; magnanimitie, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhine the more in the neare following proſperitie. And of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary part, if euill men come to the ſtage, they euer goe out (as the Tragedie writer anſwered to one that miſliked the ſhew of ſuch perſons) ſo manicled as they litle animate folkes to follow them. But the Hiſtorie beeing captiued to the trueth of a fooliſh world, is many times a terror from well-doing, and an encouragement to vnbrideled wickednes. For ſee we not valiant <hi>Milciades</hi> rot in his fetters? The iuſt <hi>Phocion</hi> and the accompliſhed <hi>Socrates,</hi> put to death like Traytors? The cruell <hi>Seuerus,</hi> liue proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perouſly? The excellent <hi>Seuerus</hi> miſerably murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red? <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Marius</hi> dying in their beds? <hi>Pompey</hi> and <hi>Cicero</hi> ſlain then when they wold haue thought exile a happineſſe? See we not vertuous <hi>Cato</hi> driuen to kill himſelfe, and Rebell <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſo aduanced, that his name yet after 1600. yeares laſteth in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt honor? And marke but euen <hi>Caeſars</hi> owne words of the forenamed <hi>Sylla,</hi> (who in that onely, did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly
<pb facs="tcp:19832:15"/> to put downe his diſhoneſt Tyrannie) <hi>Litte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras neſciuit:</hi> as if want of learning cauſed him to doo well. He ment it not by Poetrie, which not content with earthly plagues, deuiſeth new puniſhments in hell for Tyrants: nor yet by Philoſophy, which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth <hi>Occidentos eſſe,</hi> but no doubt by skill in Hiſtory, for that indeed can affoord you <hi>Cipſelus, Periander, Phalaris, Dioniſius,</hi> and I know not how many more of the ſame kennell, that ſpeed well inough in their abhominable iniuſtice of vſurpation. I conclude therfore that he excelleth hiſtorie, not onely in fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing the minde with knowledge, but in ſetting it forward to that which deſerues to be called and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted good: which ſetting forward and mouing to well doing, indeed ſetteth the Lawrell Crowne vpon the <hi>Poets</hi> as victorious, not onely of the <hi>Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> but ouer the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> howſoeuer in tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching it may be queſtionable. For ſuppoſe it be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that which I ſuppoſe with great reaſon may be denied, that the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> in reſpect of his metho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dical proceeding, teach more perfectly then the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et,</hi> yet do I thinke, that no man is ſo much <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as to compare the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> in moouing with the <hi>Poet.</hi> And that moouing is of a higher degree then teaching, it may by this appeare, that it is well nigh both the cauſe and effect of teaching. For who will be taught, if hee be not mooued with deſire to be taught? And what ſo much good doth that teaching bring foorth, (I ſpeake ſtill of morall doctrine) as that it mooueth one to do that which it doth teach. For as <hi>Aristotle</hi> ſaith, it is not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> muſt be the frute: and how <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, can be without being mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:19832:16"/> to practiſe, it is no hard matter to conſider. The <hi>Philoſopher</hi> ſheweth you the way, hee enformeth you of the particularities, as well of the tediouſnes of the way, as of the pleaſaunt lodging you ſhall haue when your iourney is ended, as of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by turnings that may diuert you from your way. But this is to no man but to him that will reade him, and reade him with attentiue ſtudious pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe, which conſtant deſire, whoſoeuer hath in him, hath alreadie paſt halfe the hardneſſe of the way: and therefore is beholding to the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,</hi> but for the other halfe. Nay truly learned men haue learnedly thought, that where once rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon hath ſo much ouer-maſtered paſsion, as that the minde hath a free deſire to doo well, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward light each minde hath in it ſelfe, is as good as a <hi>Philoſophers</hi> booke, ſince in Nature we know it is well, to doo well, and what is well, and what is euill, although not in the wordes of Art which <hi>Philoſophers</hi> beſtow vppon vs: for out of naturall conceit the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> drew it; but to be moued to doo that which wee know, or to be mooued with deſire to know. <hi>Hoc opus, hic labor est.</hi> Now therein of all Sciences I ſpeake ſtill of humane (and according to the humane conceit) is our <hi>Poet</hi> the <hi>Monarch.</hi> For hee doth not onely ſhew the way, but giueth ſo ſweete a proſpect into the way, as will entice anie man to enter into it: Nay he doth as if your iourney ſhould lye through a faire vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, at the verie firſt, giue you a cluſter of grapes, that full of that taſte, you may long to paſſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Hee beginneth not with obſcure definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:16"/> which muſt blurre the margent with inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretations, and loade the memorie with doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: but hee commeth to you with words ſet in delightfull proportion, either accompanied with, or prepared for the well enchanting skill of <hi>Muſicke,</hi> and with a tale forſooth he commeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, with a tale, which holdeth children from play, and olde men from the Chimney corner; and pretending no more, doth intend the winning of the minde from wickednes to vertue; euen as the child is often brought to take moſt wholeſome things by hiding them in ſuch other as haue a pleaſaunt taſte: which if one ſhould begin to tell them the nature of the <hi>Alloes</hi> or <hi>Rhabarbarum</hi> they ſhould receiue, wold ſooner take their phiſick at their eares then at their mouth, ſo is it in men (moſt of which, are childiſh in the beſt things, til they be cradled in their graues) glad they will be to heare the tales of <hi>Hercules, Achil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, Cyrus, Aeneas,</hi> and hearing them, muſt needes heare the right deſcription of wiſdom, value, and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice; which if they had bene barely (that is to ſay Philoſophically) ſet out, they would ſweare they be brought to ſchoole againe; that imitation whereof <hi>Poetrie</hi> is, hath the moſt conueniencie to nature of al other: inſomuch that as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſaith, thoſe things which in themſelues are horrible, as cruel battailes, vnnatural monſters, are made in poeticall imitation, delightfull. Truly I haue knowne men, that euen with reading <hi>Amadis de gaule,</hi> which God knoweth, wanteth much of a perfect <hi>Poeſie,</hi> haue found their hearts moued to the exerciſe of courteſie, liberali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and eſpecially courage. Who readeth <hi>Aeneas</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying old <hi>Anchiſes</hi> on his backe, that wiſheth not
<pb facs="tcp:19832:17"/> it were his fortune to performe ſo excellent an Act? Whom doth not thoſe words of <hi>Turnus</hi> mooue, (the Tale of <hi>Turnus</hi> hauing planted his image in the imagination) <hi>fugientem haec terra videbit? Vſqueadeone mori miſerum eſt?</hi> Wher the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> as they think ſcorne to delight, ſo muſt they be content little to mooue; ſauing wrangling whether <hi>Virtus</hi> be the chiefe or the onely good; whether the contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue or the actiue life do excell; which <hi>Plato</hi> &amp; <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> well knew: and therefore made miſtreſſe <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophie</hi> verie often borrow the masking raiment of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> For euen thoſe hard hearted euill men who thinke vertue a ſchoole name, and know no other good but <hi>indulgere genio,</hi> and therefore deſpiſe the auſtere admonitions of the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> and feele not the inward reaſon they ſtand vpon, yet will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be delighted, which is all the good, fellow <hi>Poet</hi> ſeemes to promiſe; and ſo ſteale to ſee the form of goodnes, (which ſeene, they cannot but loue) ere themſelues be aware, as if they tooke a medicine of Cheries. Infinit proofes of the ſtraunge effects of this Poeticall inuention, might be alleaged: onely two ſhall ſerue, which are ſo often remembred, as I thinke all men know them. The one of <hi>Menemus Agrippa,</hi> who when the whole people of <hi>Rome</hi> had reſolutely diuided themſelues from the <hi>Senate,</hi> with apparant ſhew of vtter ruine, though he were for that time an excellent Orator, came not amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them vpon truſt either of figuratiue ſpeeches, or cunning inſinuations, and much leſſe with farre ſet <hi>Maximes</hi> of <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> which eſpecially if they were <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonike,</hi> they muſt haue learned <hi>Geometrie</hi> before
<pb facs="tcp:19832:17"/> they could well haue conceiued: but forſooth, he behaueth himſelfe like a homely and familiar <hi>Poet.</hi> He telleth them a tale, that there was a time, when all the parts of the bodie made a mutinous conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie againſt the belly, which they thought deuoured the frutes of each others labour: they concluded they would let ſo vnprofitable a ſpender ſtarue. In the end, to be ſhort, for the tale is notorious, and as notorious that it was a tale, with puniſhing the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they plagued themſelues; this applied by him, wrought ſuch effect in the people, as I neuer red, that onely words brought foorth: but then ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine and ſo good an alteration, for vpon reaſonable conditions, a perfect reconcilement enſued. The o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Prophet, who when the holie <hi>Dauid,</hi> had ſo farre forſaken God, as to confirme A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulterie with murther, when he was to do the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſt office of a friend, in laying his owne ſhame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes; ſent by God to call againe ſo choſen a ſeruant, how doth he it? but by telling of a man whoſe beloued lambe was vngratefully taken from his boſome. The Application moſt diuinely true, but the diſcourſe it ſelfe fained; which made <hi>Dauid</hi> (I ſpeake of the ſecond and inſtrumentall cauſe) as in a glaſſe ſee his owne filthineſſe, as that heauenly Pſalme of mercie well teſtifieth. By theſe therefore examples and reaſons. I thinke it may be manifeſt, that the <hi>Poet</hi> with that ſame hand of delight, doth draw the mind more effectually then any other Art doth. And ſo a concluſion not vnfitly enſue, that as vertue is the moſt excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t reſting place for al world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly learning to make his end of, ſo <hi>Poetry</hi> being the
<pb facs="tcp:19832:18"/> moſt familiar to teach it, and moſt Princely to moue towards it, in the moſt excellent worke, is the moſt excellent workeman. But I am content not onely to decipher him by his workes (although workes in commendation and diſpraiſe, muſt euer hold a high authoritie) but more narrowly will examine his parts, ſo that (as in a man) though altogither may carrie a preſence full of maieſtie and bewtie, perchance in ſome one defectuous peece we may finde blemiſh: Now in his parts, kindes, or <hi>ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> as you liſt to tearme them, it is to be noted, that ſome <hi>Poeſies</hi> haue coupled togither two or three kindes, as the <hi>Tragicall</hi> and <hi>Comicall,</hi> whereupon is riſen the <hi>Tragicomicall,</hi> ſome in the maner haue mingled proſe and verſe, as <hi>Sanazara</hi> and <hi>Boetius;</hi> ſome haue mingled matters <hi>Heroicall</hi> and <hi>Pastorall,</hi> but that commeth all to one in this queſtion, for if ſeuered they be good, the coniunction cannot be hurtfull: therefore perchance forgetting ſome, and leauing ſome as needleſſe to be remembred. It ſhall not bee amiſſe, in a word to cite the ſpeciall kindes, to ſee what faults may be found in the right vſe of them. Is it then the Paſtorall <hi>Poeme</hi> which is miſliked? (For perchance where the hedge is low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt they will ſooneſt leape ouer) is the poore pipe diſdained, which ſomtimes out of <hi>Maelibeus</hi> mouth, can ſhewe the miſerie of people, vnder hard Lords and rauening ſouldiers? And again by <hi>Titerus,</hi> what bleſſedneſſe is deriued, to them that lie loweſt, from the goodneſſe of them that fit higheſt? Sometimes vnder the prettie tales of Woolues and ſheepe, can <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nclude the whole conſiderations of wrong doing
<pb facs="tcp:19832:18"/> and patience; ſometimes ſhew that contentions for trifles, can get but a trifling victory, wher perchance a man may ſee, that euen <hi>Alexander</hi> &amp; <hi>Darius,</hi> when they ſtraue who ſhould be Cocke of this worldes dunghill, the benefit they got, was, that the afterli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers may ſay, <hi>Haec memini &amp; victum frustra contende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re Thirſim. Ex illo Coridon, Coridon est tempore nobis.</hi> Or is it the lamenting <hi>Elegiack,</hi> which in a kinde heart would mooue rather pittie then blame, who bewaileth with the great Philoſopher <hi>Heraclitus,</hi> the weakeneſſe of mankinde, and the wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the world: who ſurely is to bee praiſed either for compaſsionate accompanying iuſt cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of lamentations, or for rightlie painting out how weake be the paſsions of wofulneſſe? Is it the bitter but wholeſome <hi>Iambick,</hi> who rubbes the galled minde, in making ſhame the Trumpet of villanie, with bolde and open crying out againſt naughtineſſe? Or the <hi>Satirick,</hi> who <hi>Omne vafer vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium ridenti tangit amico,</hi> who ſportingly, neuer leaueth, till he make a man laugh at follie; and at length aſhamed, to laugh at himſelf; which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not auoyde, without auoyding the follie? who while <hi>Circum praecordia ludit,</hi> giueth vs to feele how many headaches a paſsionate life bringeth vs to? How when all is done, <hi>Est Vlubris animus ſi nos non deficit aequus.</hi> No perchance it is the <hi>Comick,</hi> whom naughtie Play-makers and ſtage-keepers, haue iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly made odious. To the arguments of abuſe, I will after anſwer, onely thus much now is to be ſaid, that the <hi>Comedy</hi> is an imitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon errors of our life, which he repreſenteth in the moſt ridiculous &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:19832:19"/> ſcornfull ſort that may be: ſo as it is impoſsible that any beholder can be content to be ſuch a one. Now as in <hi>Geometrie,</hi> the oblique muſt be knowne as well as the right, and in <hi>Arithmetick,</hi> the odde as well as the euen, ſo in the actions of our life, who ſeeth not the filthineſſe of euill, wanteth a great foile to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the bewtie of vertue. This doth the Comaedie handle ſo in our priuate and domeſticall matters, as with hearing it, wee get as it were an experience what is to be looked for of a niggardly <hi>Demea,</hi> of a craftie <hi>Dauus,</hi> of a flattering <hi>Gnato,</hi> of a vain-glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Thraſo:</hi> and not onely to know what effects are to be expected, but to know who be ſuch, by the ſignifying badge giuen them by the <hi>Comaedient.</hi> And litle reaſon hath any man to ſay, that men learne the euill by ſeeing it ſo ſet out, ſince as I ſaid before, there is no man liuing, but by the force truth hath in nature, no ſooner ſeeth theſe men play their parts, but wiſheth them in <hi>Piſtrinum,</hi> although perchance the ſack of his owne faults lie ſo behinde his backe, that he ſeeth not himſelfe to dance the ſame meaſure: wherto yet nothing can more open his eies, then to ſee his owne actions contemptibly ſet forth. So that the right vſe of <hi>Comaedie,</hi> will I thinke, by no bodie be blamed; and much leſſe of the high and excellent <hi>Tragedie,</hi> that openeth the greateſt woundes, and ſheweth forth the <hi>Vlcers</hi> that are couered with <hi>Tiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue,</hi> that maketh Kings feare to be Tyrants, and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants manifeſt their tyrannicall humours, that with ſturring the affects of <hi>Admiration</hi> and <hi>Comiſeration,</hi> teacheth the vncertaintie of this world, and vppon how weak foundations guilden roofes are builded:
<pb facs="tcp:19832:19"/> that maketh vs know, <hi>Qui ſcaeptra ſaeuus duro imperio regit, Timet timentes, metus in authorem redit.</hi> But how much it can moue, <hi>Plutarch</hi> yeeldeth a notable teſtimonie of the abhominable Tyrant <hi>Alexander Pheraeus,</hi> from whoſe eyes a <hi>Tragedie</hi> well made and repreſented, drew abundance of teares, who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all pittie had murthered infinite numbers, and ſome of his owne bloud: ſo as he that was not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to make matters for <hi>Tragedies,</hi> yet could not reſiſt the ſweete violence of a <hi>Tragedie.</hi> And if it wrought no further good in him, it was, that he in deſpight of himſelf, withdrew himſelfe from hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening to that which might mollifie his hardened heart. But it is not the <hi>Tragedie</hi> they do miſlike, for it were too abſurd to caſt our ſo excellent a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of whatſoeuer is moſt woorthie to be learned. Is it the <hi>Lyricke</hi> that moſte diſpleaſeth, who with his tuned <hi>Lyre</hi> and well accorded voice, giueth praiſe, the reward of vertue, to vertuous acts? who giueth morall preceptes and naturall Problemes, who ſometime raiſeth vp his voyce to the height of the heauens, in ſinging the laudes of the immortall God? Certainly I muſt confeſſe mine owne barbarouſneſſe, I neuer heard the old Song of <hi>Percy</hi> and <hi>Duglas,</hi> that I founde not my heart mooued more then with a Trumpet; and yet is it ſung but by ſome blinde Crowder, with no rougher voyce, then rude ſtile: which being ſo euill apparelled in the duſt and Cobwebbes of that vnciuill age, what would it worke, trimmed in the gorgious eloquence of <hi>Pindare?</hi> In <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> I haue ſeene it the manner at all Feaſtes and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:19832:20"/> ſuch like meetings, to haue ſongs of their ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors valure, which that right ſouldierlike nation, think one of the chiefeſt kindlers of braue courage. The incomperable <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> did not onelie carrie that kinde of <hi>Muſicke</hi> euer with them to the field, but euen at home, as ſuch ſongs were made, ſo were they all content to be ſingers of them: when the luſtie men were to tell what they did, the old men what they had done, and the yoong what they would doo. And where a man may ſay that <hi>Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dare</hi> many times praiſeth highly Victories of ſmall moment, rather matters of ſport then vertue, as it may be anſwered, it was the fault of the <hi>Poet,</hi> and not of the <hi>Poetrie;</hi> ſo indeed the chiefe fault was, in the time and cuſtome of the <hi>Greekes,</hi> who ſet thoſe toyes at ſo high a price, that <hi>Phillip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> reckoned a horſe-race wonne at <hi>Olympus,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong his three fearefull felicities. But as the vnimitable <hi>Pindare</hi> often did, ſo is that kind moſt capable and moſt fit, to awake the thoughts from the ſleepe of idleneſſe, to embrace honourable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſes. Their reſts the <hi>Heroicall,</hi> whoſe verie name I thinke ſhould daunt all backbiters. For by what conceit can a tongue bee directed to ſpeake euil of that which draweth with him no leſſe cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions then <hi>Achilles, Cirus, Aeneas, Turnus, Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deus, Rinaldo,</hi> who doeth not onely teache and mooue to a truth, but teacheth and mooueth to the moſt high and excellent truth: who maketh magnanimitie and iuſtice, ſhine through all miſtie fearefulneſſe and foggie deſires. Who if the ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:19832:20"/> of <hi>Plato</hi> and <hi>Tully</hi> bee true, that who could ſee vertue, woulde bee woonderfullie rauiſhed with the loue of her bewtie. This man ſetteth her out to make her more louely in her holliday apparrell, to the eye of anie that will daine, not to diſdaine vntill they vnderſtand. But if any thing be alreadie ſaid in the defence of ſweete <hi>Poetrie,</hi> all concurreth to the mainteining the <hi>Heroicall,</hi> which is not onelie a kinde, but the beſt and moſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed kindes of <hi>Poetrie.</hi> For as the Image of each Action ſtirreth and inſtructeth the minde, ſo the loſtie Image of ſuch woorthies, moſte en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flameth the minde with deſire to bee woorthie: and enformes with counſaile how to bee woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie. Onely let <hi>Aeneas</hi> bee worne in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blet of your memorie, how hee gouerneth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the ruine of his Countrey, in the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing his olde Father, and carrying away his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Ceremonies, in obeying Gods Commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to leaue <hi>Dido,</hi> though not onelie all paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate kindneſſe, but euen the humane conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of vertuous gratefulneſſe, would haue cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued other of him: how in ſtormes, how in ſports, how in warre, how in peace, how a fugitiue, how victorious, how beſieged, how beſieging, how to ſtraungers, how to Allies, how to ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, how to his owne. Laſtly, how in his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde ſelfe, and howe in his outward gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I thinke in a minde moſte preiudiced with a preiudicating humour, Hee will bee founde in excellencie fruitefull. Yea as <hi>Horace</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19832:21"/> ſaith, <hi>Melius Chriſippo &amp; Grantore:</hi> but truly I ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin it falleth out with theſe Poet-whippers, as with ſome good women who often are ſicke, but in faith they cannot tel where. So the name of <hi>Poetrie</hi> is odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to them, but neither his cauſe nor effects, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſumme that containes him, nor the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities deſcending from him, giue any faſt handle to their carping diſpraiſe. Since then <hi>Poetrie</hi> is of al hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane learnings the moſt ancient, and of moſt father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly antiquitie, as from whence other learnings haue taken their beginnings; Since it is ſo vniuerſall, that no learned nation doth deſpiſe it, nor barbarous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is without it; Since both <hi>Romane</hi> &amp; <hi>Greeke</hi> gaue ſuch diuine names vnto it, the one of propheſying, the other of making; and that indeed that name of making is fit for him, conſidering, that where all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Arts retain themſelues within their ſubiect, and receiue as it were their being from it. The <hi>Poet</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, onely bringeth his own ſtuffe, and doth not learn a Conceit out of a matter, but maketh matter for a Conceit. Since neither his deſcription, nor end, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining any euill, the thing deſcribed cannot be euil; ſince his effects be ſo good as to teach goodnes, and delight the learners of it; ſince therein (namely in morall doctrine the chiefe of all knowledges) hee doth not onely farre paſſe the <hi>Historian,</hi> but for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructing is well nigh comparable to the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> for mouing, leaueth him behind him. Since the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcripture (wherein there is no vncleanneſſe) hath whole parts in it Poeticall, and that euen our Sauior Chriſt vouchſafed to vſe the flowers of it: ſince all his kindes are not onely in their vnited formes, but
<pb facs="tcp:19832:21"/> in their ſeuered diſſections fully commendable, I thinke, (and thinke I thinke rightly) the Lawrell Crowne appointed for tryumphant Captaines, doth worthily of all other learnings, honour the <hi>Poets</hi> tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph. But bicauſe we haue eares as well as toongs, and that the lighteſt reaſons that may be, will ſeeme to waigh greatly, if nothing be put in the counter-ballance, let vs heare, and as well as we can, ponder what obiections be made againſt this Art, which may be woorthie either of yeelding, or anſwering. Firſt truly I note, not onely in theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Poet-ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but in all that kind of people who ſeek a praiſe, by diſpraiſing others, that they do prodigally ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a great many wandring words in quips and ſcoffes, carping and taunting at each thing, which by ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſpleene, may ſtaie the brain from a through beholding the worthineſſe of the ſubiect. Thoſe kind of obiections, as they are full of a verie idle ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, ſince there is nothing of ſo ſacred a maieſtie, but that an itching toong may rub it ſelfe vpon it, ſo deſerue they no other anſwer, but in ſteed of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the ieaſt, to laugh at the ieaſter. We know a playing wit can praiſe the diſcretion of an Aſſe, the comfortablenes of being in debt, and the iolly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of being ſicke of the plague. So of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary ſide, if we will turne <hi>Ouids</hi> verſe, <hi>Vt lateat vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, prox imitate mali,</hi> that good lye hid, in nearneſſe of the euill. <hi>Agrippa</hi> will be as mery in ſhewing the vanitie of Science, as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> was in the commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of folly: neither ſhal any man or matter, eſcape ſome touch of theſe ſmiling Raylers. But for <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa,</hi> they had an other foundation then
<pb facs="tcp:19832:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19832:22"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:19832:23"/> the ſuperficiall part would promiſe. Marry theſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſaunt fault-finders, who will correct the <hi>Verbe,</hi> before they vnderſtand the <hi>Nowne,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute others knowledge, before they confirme their owne, I would haue them onely remember, that ſcoffing commeth not of wiſedome; ſo as the beſt title in true Engliſh they get with their meriments, is to be called good fooles: for ſo haue our graue forefathers euer tearmed that humorous kinde of ieſters. But that which giueth greateſt ſcope to their ſcorning humor, is ryming and verſing. It is alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſaid (and as I thinke truly ſaid) it is not ryming and verſing that maketh <hi>Poeſie:</hi> One may be a <hi>Poet</hi> without verſing, and a verſefier without <hi>Poetrie.</hi> But yet preſuppoſe it were inſeperable, as indeed it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth <hi>Scalliger</hi> iudgeth truly, it were an inſeperable commendation. For if <hi>Oratio,</hi> next to <hi>Ratio,</hi> Speech next to Reaſon, be the greateſt gift beſtowed vpon <hi>Mortalitie,</hi> that cannot bee praiſeleſſe, which doth moſt poliſh that bleſsing of ſpeech; which conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth each word not onely as a man may ſay by his forcible qualitie, but by his beſt meaſured quantity: carrying euen in themſelues a <hi>Harmonie,</hi> without perchance number, meaſure, order, proportion, be in our time growne odious. But laie aſide the iuſt praiſe it hath, by being the onely fit ſpeech for <hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, (Muſicke</hi> I ſay the moſt diuine ſtriker of the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) Thus much is vndoubtedly true, that if rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding be fooliſh without remembring, Memorie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the onely treaſure of knowledge, thoſe words which are fitteſt for memory, are likewiſe moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient for knowledge. Now that Verſe far excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
<pb facs="tcp:19832:23"/> Proſe, in the knitting vp of the memorie, the reaſon is manifeſt, the words (beſides their delight, which hath a great affinitie to memorie) being ſo ſet as one cannot be loſt, but the whole woorke failes: which accuſing it ſelfe, calleth the remembrance back to it ſelfe, and ſo moſt ſtrongly confirmeth it. Beſides one word, ſo as it were begetting an other, as be it in rime or meaſured verſe, by the former a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall haue a neare geſſe to the follower. Laſtly euen they that haue taught the Art of memory, haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed nothing ſo apt for it, as a certain roome diuided into many places, well &amp; throughly knowne: Now that hath the verſe in effect perfectly, euerie word hauing his natural ſeat, which ſeat muſt needs make the word remembred. But what needes more in a thing ſo knowne to all men. Who is it that euer was ſcholler, that doth not carry away ſom verſes of <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gil, Horace,</hi> or <hi>Cato,</hi> which in his youth hee learned, and eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to his old age ſerue him for hourely leſſons; as <hi>Percontatorem fugito nam garrulus idem est, Dum tibi quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> placet credula turba ſumas.</hi> But the fitnes it hath for memorie, is notably prooued by all deliuerie of Arts, wherein for the moſt part, from <hi>Grammer,</hi> to <hi>Logick, Mathematickes, Phiſick,</hi> and the reſt, the Rules chiefly neceſſaie to be borne away, are compiled in verſes. So that verſe being in it ſelfe ſweet and order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and being beſt for memorie, the onely handle of knowledge, it muſt be in ieſt that any man can ſpeak againſt it. Now then goe we to the moſt important imputations laid to the poore <hi>Poets,</hi> for ought I can yet learne, they are theſe. Firſt, that there beeing manie other more frutefull knowledges, a man
<pb facs="tcp:19832:24"/> might better ſpend his time in them, then in this. Secondly, that it is the mother of lyes. Thirdly, that it is the nurſe of abuſe, infecting vs with many peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent deſires, with a <hi>Sirens</hi> ſweetneſſe, drawing the minde to the Serpents taile of ſinfull fanſies; and herein eſpecially <hi>Comedies</hi> giue the largeſt field to eare, as <hi>Chawcer</hi> ſaith, how both in other nations and in ours, before <hi>Poets</hi> did ſoften vs, we were full of courage giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to martial exerciſes, the pillers of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like libertie, and not lulled a ſleepe in ſhadie idlenes, with <hi>Poets</hi> paſtimes. And laſtly and chiefly, they cry out with open mouth as if they had ouerſhot <hi>Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood,</hi> that <hi>Plato</hi> baniſhed them out of his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth. Truly this is much, if there be much truth in it. Firſt to the firſt. That a man might better ſpend his time, is a reaſon indeed: but it doth as they ſay, but <hi>petere principium.</hi> For if it be, as I affirme, that no learning is ſo good, as that which teacheth and moueth to vertue, and that none can both teach and moue thereto ſo much as <hi>Poeſie,</hi> then is the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion manifeſt; that incke and paper cannot be to a more profitable purpoſe imployed. And certainly though a man ſhould graunt their firſt aſſumption, it ſhould follow (mee thinks) very vnwillingly, that good is not good, becauſe better is better. But I ſtill and vtterly deny, that there is ſprung out of earth a more fruitfull knowledge. To the ſecond therfore, that they ſhould be the principall lyers, I anſwere <hi>Paradoxically,</hi> but truly, I think truly: that of all wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vnder the Sunne, the <hi>Poet</hi> is the leaſt lyer: and though he wold, as a <hi>Poet</hi> can ſcarcely be a lyer. The <hi>Astronomer</hi> with his couſin the <hi>Geometrician,</hi> can
<pb facs="tcp:19832:24"/> hardly eſcape, when they take vpon them to mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure the height of the ſtarres. How often thinke you do the <hi>Phiſitians</hi> lie, when they auerre things good for ſickneſſes, which afterwards ſend <hi>Charon</hi> a great number of ſoules drownd in a potion, before they come to his Ferrie? And no leſſe of the reſt, which take vpon them to affirme. Now for the <hi>Poet,</hi> he no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing affirmeth, and therefore neuer lieth: for as I take it, to lie, is to affirme that to bee true, which is falſe. So as the other <hi>Artistes,</hi> and eſpecially the <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian,</hi> affirming manie things, can in the clowdie knowledge of mankinde, hardly eſcape from manie lies. But the <hi>Poet</hi> as I ſaid before, neuer affirmeth, the <hi>Poet</hi> neuer maketh any Circles about your imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, to coniure you to beleeue for true, what he wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth: he citeth not authorities of other hiſtories, but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for his entrie, calleth the ſweete <hi>Muſes</hi> to inſpire vnto him a good inuention. In troth, not laboring to tel you what is, or is not, but what ſhould, or ſhould not be. And therefore though he recount things not true, yet becauſe he telleth them not for true, he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not: without we will ſay, that <hi>Nathan</hi> lied in his ſpeech before alleaged to <hi>Dauid,</hi> which as a wicked man durſt ſcarce ſay, ſo think I none ſo ſimple, wold ſay, that <hi>Eſope</hi> lied, in the tales of his beaſts: for who thinketh that <hi>Eſope</hi> wrote it for actually true, were wel worthie to haue his name Cronicled among the beaſts he writeth of. What childe is there, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to a play, and ſeeing <hi>Thebes</hi> written in great let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters vpon an old doore, doth beleeue that it is <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes?</hi> If then a man can arriue to the childes age, to know that the <hi>Poets</hi> perſons and dooings, are but
<pb facs="tcp:19832:25"/> pictures, what ſhould be, and not ſtories what haue bin, they will neuer giue the lie to things not Affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiuely, but Allegorically and figuratiuely writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; and therefore as in hiſtorie looking for truth, they may go away full fraught with falſhood: So in <hi>Poeſie,</hi> looking but for fiction, they ſhall vſe the narration but as an imaginatiue ground plat of a profitable inuention. But hereto is replied, that the <hi>Poets</hi> giue names to men they write of, which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueth a conceit of an actuall truth, and ſo not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing true, prooueth a falſhood. And dooth the <hi>Lawier</hi> lye, then when vnder the names of <hi>Iohn</hi> of the <hi>Stile,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> of the <hi>Nokes,</hi> hee putteth his Caſe? But that is eaſily anſwered, their naming of men, is but to make their picture the more liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not to build anie Hiſtorie. Painting men, they cannot leaue men nameleſſe: wee ſee, wee cannot plaie at Cheſtes, but that wee muſt giue names to our Cheſſemen; and yet mee thinkes he were a verie partiall Champion of truth, that would ſay wee lyed, for giuing a peece of wood the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerende title of a Biſhop. The <hi>Poet</hi> nameth <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> and <hi>Aeneas,</hi> no other way, then to ſhewe what men of their fames, fortunes, and eſtares, ſhould doo. Their third is, how much it abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth mens wit, training it to wanton ſinfulneſſe, and luſtfull loue. For indeed that is the principall if not onely abuſe, I can heare alleadged. They ſay the <hi>Comedies</hi> rather teach then reprehend amorous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceits. They ſay the <hi>Lirick</hi> is larded with paſsionat <hi>Sonets,</hi> the <hi>Elegiack</hi> weeps the want of his miſtreſſe, and that euen to the <hi>Heroical, Cupid</hi> hath ambitiouſly
<pb facs="tcp:19832:25"/> climed. Alas Loue, I would thou couldeſt as wel de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend thy ſelfe, as thou canſt offend others: I would thoſe on whom thou doeſt attend, could either put thee away, or yeeld good reaſon why they keepe thee. But grant loue of bewtie to be a beaſtly fault, although it be verie hard, ſince onely man and no beaſt hath that gift to diſcerne bewtie, graunt that louely name of loue to deſerue all hatefull repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, although euen ſome of my maiſters the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers</hi> ſpent a good deale of their Lampoyle in ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting foorth the excellencie of it, graunt I ſay, what they will haue graunted, that not onelie loue, but luſt, but vanitie, but if they liſt ſcurrilitie, poſſeſſe manie leaues of the <hi>Poets</hi> bookes, yet thinke I, when this is graunted, they will finde their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence may with good manners put the laſt words foremoſt; and not ſay, that <hi>Poetrie</hi> abuſeth mans wit, but that mans wit abuſeth <hi>Poetrie.</hi> For I will not denie, but that mans wit may make <hi>Poeſie,</hi> which ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſome learned haue defined figuring foorth good things to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which doth contrariwiſe infect the fancie with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woorthie obiects, as the Painter ſhould giue to the eye either ſome excellent perſpectiue, or ſome fine Picture fit for building or fortification, or containing in it ſome notable example, as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> ſacrificing his ſonne <hi>Iſaack, Iudith</hi> killing <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lofernes, Dauid</hi> fighting with <hi>Golias,</hi> may leaue thoſe, and pleaſe an ill pleaſed eye with wanton ſhewes of better hidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> matters. But what, ſhal the abuſe of a thing, make the right vſe odious? Nay truly though
<pb facs="tcp:19832:26"/> I yeeld, that <hi>Poeſie</hi> may not onely be abuſed, but that being abuſed by the reaſon of his ſweete charming force, it can do more hurt then anie other armie of words: yet ſhall it be ſo farre from concluding, that the abuſe ſhould giue reproach to the abuſed, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe, it is a good reaſon, that whatſoeuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing abuſed, doth moſt harme, being rightly vſed (and vpon the right vſe, ech thing receiues his title) doth moſt good. Do we not ſee skill of Phiſicke the beſt ramper to our often aſſaulted bodies, being abuſed, teach poyſon the moſt violent deſtroyer? Doth not knowledge of Law, whoſe end is, to euen &amp; right all things, being abuſed, grow the crooked foſterer of horrible iniuries? Doth not (to go to the higheſt) Gods word abuſed, breede hereſie, and his name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, become blaſphemie? Truly a Needle cannot do much hurt, and as truly (with leaue of Ladies be it ſpoken) it cannot do much good. With a ſwoord thou maiſt kill thy Father, and with a ſwoord thou maiſt defende thy Prince and Countrey: ſo that, as in their calling <hi>Poets,</hi> fathers of lies, they ſaid nothing, ſo in this their argument of abuſe, they prooue the commendation. They alledge herewith, that before <hi>Poets</hi> began to be in price, our Nation had ſet their hearts delight vppon action, and not imagination, rather doing things worthie to be written, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting things fit to be done. What that before time was, I think ſcarcely <hi>Spinx</hi> can tell: ſince no meme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie is ſo ancient, that hath not the precedens of <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie.</hi> And certain it is, that in our plaineſt homelines, yet neuer was the <hi>Albion</hi> Nation without <hi>Poetrie.</hi> Marry this Argument, though it be leuiled againſt
<pb facs="tcp:19832:26"/> 
               <hi>Poetrie,</hi> yet is it indeed a chain-ſhot againſt all lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or bookiſhnes, as they commonly terme it. Of ſuch mind were certaine <hi>Gothes,</hi> of whom it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that hauing in the ſpoile of a famous Cittie, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken a faire Librarie, one hangman belike fit to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the frutes of their wits, who had murthered a great number of bodies, woulde haue ſet fire in it. No ſaid an other verie grauely, take heed what you do, for while they are buſie about thoſe toyes, wee ſhall with more leiſure conquere their Countries. This indeed is the ordinarie doctrine of ignorance, and many words ſometimes I haue heard ſpent in it: but bicauſe this reaſon is generally againſt al lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, as wel as <hi>Poetrie,</hi> or rather all learning but <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie,</hi> becauſe it were too large a digreſsion to handle it, or at leaſt too ſuperfluous, ſince it is manifeſt that all gouernment of action is to be gotten by know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and knowledge beſt, by gathering manie knowledges, which is reading; I onely with <hi>Horace,</hi> to him that is of that opinion, <hi>Iubio ſtultum eſſe liben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> for as for <hi>Poetrie</hi> it ſelfe, it is the freeſt from this obiection, for <hi>Poetrie</hi> is the Companion of Camps. I dare vndertake, <hi>Orlando Furioſo,</hi> or honeſt king <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thure,</hi> will neuer diſpleaſe a ſouldier: but the quid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie of <hi>Ens</hi> &amp; <hi>Prima materia,</hi> will hardly agree with a Corcelet. And therefore as I ſaid in the beginning, euen <hi>Turkes</hi> and <hi>Tartars,</hi> are delighted with <hi>Poets. Homer</hi> a <hi>Creeke,</hi> flouriſhed, before <hi>Greece</hi> flouriſhed: and if to a ſlight coniecture, a coniecture may bee appoſed, truly it may ſeem, that as by him their lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tooke almoſt their firſt light of knowledge, ſo their actiue men, receiued their firſt motions of
<pb facs="tcp:19832:27"/> courage. Onely <hi>Alexanders</hi> example may ſerue, who by <hi>Plutarche</hi> is accounted of ſuch vertue, that fortune was not his guide, but his footeſtoole, whoſe Acts ſpeake for him, though <hi>Plutarche</hi> did not: indeede the <hi>Phaenix</hi> of warlike Princes. This <hi>Alexander,</hi> left his Schoolemaiſter liuing <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stotle</hi> behinde him, but tooke dead <hi>Homer</hi> with him. Hee put the Philoſopher <hi>Callisthenes</hi> to death, for his ſeeming Philoſophicall, indeed mutinous ſtubbornneſſe, but the chiefe thing hee was euer heard to wiſh for, was, that <hi>Homer</hi> had bene aliue. Hee well founde hee receiued more brauerie of minde by the paterne of <hi>Achilles,</hi> then by hearing the definition of fortitude. And therefore if <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> miſliked <hi>Fuluius</hi> for carrying <hi>Ennius</hi> with him to the field, It may be anſwered, that if <hi>Cato</hi> miſli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked it, the Noble <hi>Fuluius</hi> liked it, or elſe he had not done it; for it was not the excellent <hi>Cato Vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencis,</hi> whoſe authoritie I would much more haue reuerenced: But it was the former, in truth a bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter puniſher of faultes, but elſe a man that had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſacrificed to the <hi>Graces.</hi> Hee miſliked and cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out againſt all Greeke learning, and yet being foure ſcore yeares olde beganne to learne it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like fearing that <hi>Pluto</hi> vnderſtood not Latine. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the <hi>Romane</hi> lawes allowed no perſon to bee carried to the warres, but hee that was in the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers Role. And therefore though <hi>Cato</hi> miſliked his vnmuſtred perſon, he miſliked not his worke. And if hee had, <hi>Scipio Naſica</hi> (iudged by common conſent the beſt <hi>Romane</hi>) loued him: both the other <hi>Scipio</hi> brothers, who had by their vertues no leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:19832:27"/> ſurnames then of <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Affricke,</hi> ſo loued him, that they cauſed his bodie to be buried in their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulture. So as <hi>Catoes</hi> authoritie beeing but againſt his perſon, and that anſwered with ſo farre grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then himſelfe, is herein of no validitie. But now indeede my burthen is great, that <hi>Plato</hi> his name is laide vppon mee, whom I muſt confeſſe of all <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> I haue euer eſteemed moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of reuerence; and with good reaſon, ſince of all <hi>Philoſophers</hi> hee is the moſt <hi>Poeticall:</hi> yet if hee will defile the fountaine out of which his flowing ſtreames haue proceeded, let vs boldly examine with what reaſons hee did it. Firſt truly a man might maliciouſly obiect, that <hi>Plato</hi> being a <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher,</hi> was a naturall enemy of <hi>Poets.</hi> For indeede after the <hi>Philoſophers</hi> had picked out of the ſweete miſteries of <hi>Poetrie,</hi> the right diſcerning true points of knowledge: they foorthwith putting it in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thode, and making a Schoole Art of that which the <hi>Poets</hi> did onely teach by a diuine delightfulnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to ſpurne at their guides, like vngratefull Prentices, were not content to ſet vp ſhop for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but ſought by all meanes to diſcredit their maiſters, which by the force of delight being bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them, the leſſe they could ouerthrow them, the more they hated them. For indeed they found for <hi>Homer,</hi> ſeuen Cities ſtraue who ſhould haue him for their Cittizen, where many Cities baniſhed <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers,</hi> as not fit members to liue among them. For onely repeating certaine of <hi>Euripides</hi> verſes, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Atheniens</hi> had their liues ſaued of the <hi>Sira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſans,</hi> where the <hi>Atheniens</hi> themſelues thought
<pb facs="tcp:19832:28"/> many <hi>Philoſophers</hi> vnworthie to liue. Certaine <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets,</hi> as <hi>Simonides,</hi> and <hi>Pindarus,</hi> had ſo preuailed with <hi>Hiero</hi> the firſt, that of a Tyrant they made him a iuſt King: where <hi>Plato</hi> could do ſo little with <hi>Dioniſius,</hi> that he himſelfe of a <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> was made a ſlaue. But who ſhould do thus, I confeſſe ſhould requite the obiections made againſt <hi>Poets,</hi> with like cauil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations againſt <hi>Philoſophers:</hi> as likewiſe one ſhould do, that ſhould bid one read <hi>Phaedrus</hi> or <hi>Simpoſium</hi> in <hi>Plato,</hi> or the diſcourſe of loue in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> and ſee whether any <hi>Poet</hi> do authoriſe abhominable filthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe as they doo. Againe, a man might aske, out of what Common-wealth <hi>Plato</hi> doth baniſh them, in ſooth, thence where he himſelfe alloweth commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of women. So as belike this baniſhment grew not for effeminate wantonneſſe, ſince little ſhould Poetical <hi>Sonnets</hi> be hurtful, when a man might haue what woman he liſted. But I honor Philoſophicall inſtructions, and bleſſe the wits which bred them: ſo as they be not abuſed, which is likewiſe ſtretched to <hi>Poetrie.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe ſets a watch-word vppon <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> indeed vppon the abuſe. So doth <hi>Plato</hi> vppon the abuſe, not vpon <hi>Poetrie. Plato</hi> found fault that the <hi>Poettes</hi> of his time, filled the worlde with wrng opinions of the Gods, making light tales of that vnſpotted eſſence; and therfore wold not haue the youth depraued with ſuch opinions: heerein may much be ſaid; let this ſuffice. The <hi>Poets</hi> did not induce ſuch opinions, but did imitate thoſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alreadie induced. For all the <hi>Greeke</hi> ſtories can well teſtifie, that the verie religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that time, ſtood vpon many, and many faſhioned Gods: Not taught
<pb facs="tcp:19832:28"/> ſo by <hi>Poets,</hi> but followed according to their nature of imitation. Who liſt may read in <hi>Plutarch,</hi> the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes of <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris,</hi> of the cauſe why Oracles ceaſed, of the diuine prouidence, &amp; ſee whether the <hi>Theology</hi> of that nation, ſtood not vpon ſuch dreams, which the <hi>Poets</hi> indeede ſuperſtitiouſly obſerued. And truly ſince they had not the light of Chriſt, did much better in it, then the <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> who ſhaking off ſuperſtition, brought in <hi>Atheiſme. Plato</hi> therfore, whoſe authoritie, I had much rather iuſtly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſture, then vniuſtly reſiſt: ment not in generall of <hi>Poets,</hi> in thoſe words of which <hi>Iulius Scaliger</hi> ſaith; <hi>Qua au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritate barbari quidam at<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> hiſpidi abuti velint ad poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas è rep. Exigendos.</hi> But only ment to driue out thoſe wrong opinions of the Deitie: wherof now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further law, <hi>Christianitie</hi> hath taken away all the hurtful beliefe, perchance as he thought nouriſhed by then eſteemed <hi>Poets.</hi> And a man need go no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then to <hi>Plato</hi> himſelfe to knowe his meaning: who in his Dialogue called <hi>Ion,</hi> giueth high, and rightly, diuine commendation vnto <hi>Poetrie.</hi> So as <hi>Plato</hi> baniſhing the abuſe, not the thing, not bani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing it, but giuing due honour to it, ſhall be our Patron, and not our aduerſarie. For indeed, I had much rather, ſince truly I may do it, ſhew their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaking of <hi>Plato,</hi> vnder whoſe Lyons skinne, they would make an Aſlike braying againſt <hi>Poeſie,</hi> then go about to ouerthrow his authoritie; whome the wiſer a man is, the more iuſt cauſe he ſhall finde to haue in admiration: eſpecially ſince he attributeth vnto <hi>Poeſie,</hi> more then my ſelfe do; namely, to be a verie inſpiring of a diuine force, farre aboue mans
<pb facs="tcp:19832:29"/> wit, as in the forenamed Dialogue is apparant. Of the other ſide, who would ſhew the honours haue bene by the beſt ſort of iudgements graunted them, a whole ſea of examples woulde preſent them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues; <hi>Alexanders, Caeſars, Scipioes,</hi> all fauourers of <hi>Poets: Laelius,</hi> called the Romane <hi>Socrates</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe a <hi>Poet;</hi> ſo as part of <hi>Heautontimoroumenon</hi> in <hi>Terence,</hi> was ſuppoſed to bee made by him. And euen the Greeke <hi>Socrates,</hi> whome <hi>Appollo</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed to bee the onely wiſe man, is ſaid to haue ſpent part of his olde time in putting <hi>Eſopes</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles into verſes. And therefore full euill ſhould it become his ſcholler <hi>Plato,</hi> to put ſuch words in his maiſters mouth againſt <hi>Poets.</hi> But what needs more? <hi>Aristotle</hi> writes the Arte of <hi>Poeſie,</hi> and why, if it ſhould not bee written? <hi>Plutarche</hi> tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the vſe to bee gathered of them, and how, if they ſhould not bee reade? And who reades <hi>Plutarches</hi> either Hiſtorie or <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> ſhall finde hee trimmeth both their garments with gardes of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> But I liſt not to defend <hi>Poeſie</hi> with the helpe of his vnderling <hi>Historiographie.</hi> Let it ſuffice to haue ſhewed, it is a fit ſoyle for praiſe to dwell vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon: and what diſpraiſe may ſet vppon it, is ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eaſily ouercome, or transformed into iuſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. So that ſince the excellencies of it, may bee ſo eaſily and ſo iuſtly confirmed, and the lowe creeping obiections ſo ſoone trodden downe, it not beeing an Art of lyes, but of true doctrine; not of effoeminateneſſe, but of notable ſtirring of courage; not of abuſing mans wit, but of ſtrengthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning mans wit; not baniſhed, but honored by <hi>Plato;</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19832:29"/> Let vs rather plant more Lawrels for to ingarland the <hi>Poets</hi> heads (which honor of being Lawreate, as beſides them onely triumphant Captaines were, is a ſufficient authoritie to ſhewe the price they ought to bee held in) then ſuffer the ill ſauoured breath of ſuch wrong ſpeakers once to blow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the cleare ſprings of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> But ſince I haue runne ſo long a Carrier in this matter, me thinkes before I giue my penne a full ſtoppe, it ſhall be but a litle more loſt time, to enquire why England the Mother of excellent mindes ſhould be growne ſo hard a ſtepmother to <hi>Poets,</hi> who certainely in wit ought to paſſe all others, ſince all onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from their wit, beeing indeed makers of themſelues, not takers of others. How can I but exclaime. <hi>Muſa mihi cauſas memoria quo numine laeſo,</hi> Sweete <hi>Poeſie</hi> that hath aunciently had Kings, Emperours, Senatours, great Captaines, ſuch as beſides a thouſandes others, <hi>Dauid, Adrian, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phocles, Germanicus,</hi> not onelie to fauour <hi>Poets,</hi> but to bee <hi>Poets:</hi> and of our nearer times, can preſent for her Patrons, a <hi>Robert</hi> King of <hi>Scicill,</hi> the great King <hi>Fraunces</hi> of <hi>Fraunce,</hi> King <hi>Iames</hi> of <hi>Scotland;</hi> ſuch Cardinalls as <hi>Bembus,</hi> and <hi>Bibiena;</hi> ſuche fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Preachers and Teachers, as <hi>Beza</hi> and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanchchon;</hi> ſo learned <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> as <hi>Fracasto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,</hi> and <hi>Scaliger;</hi> ſo great Orators, as <hi>Pontanus,</hi> and <hi>Muretus;</hi> ſo pearcing wits, as <hi>George Bucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan;</hi> ſo graue Counſailours, as beſides manie, but before all, that <hi>Hoſpitall</hi> of <hi>Fraunce;</hi> then whome I thinke that Realme neuer brought forth
<pb facs="tcp:19832:30"/> a more accompliſhed iudgement, more firmly buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vertue: I ſay theſe with numbers of others, not onely to read others <hi>Poeſies,</hi> but to <hi>poetiſe</hi> for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers reading; that <hi>Poeſie</hi> thus embraced in all other places, ſhould onely finde in our time a hard wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in England. I thinke the verie earth laments it, and therefore deckes our ſoyle with fewer Lawrels then it was accuſtomed. For heretofore, <hi>Poets</hi> haue in England alſo flouriſhed: and which is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, euen in thoſe times when the Trumpet of <hi>Mars</hi> did ſonnd lowdeſt. And now that an ouer faint qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe ſhould ſeeme to ſtrowe the houſe for <hi>Poets.</hi> They are almoſt in as good reputation, as the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tebanckes</hi> at <hi>Venice.</hi> Truly euen that, as of the one ſide it giueth great praiſe to <hi>Poeſie,</hi> which like <hi>Venus</hi> (but to better purpoſe) had rather be troubled in the net with <hi>Mars,</hi> then enioy the homely quiet of <hi>Vulcan.</hi> So ſerueth it for a peece of a reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, why they are leſſe gratefull to idle England, which now can ſcarce en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the paine of a penne. Vpon this neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that baſe men with ſeruill wits vndertake it, who thinke it inough if they can be rewarded of the Printer: and ſo as <hi>Epaminandas</hi> is ſaid with the honor of his vertue to haue made an Office, by his exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing it, which before was contemtible, to become highly reſpected: ſo theſe men no more but ſetting their names to it, by their own diſgracefulneſſe, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace the moſt gracefull <hi>Poesie.</hi> For now as if all the <hi>Muſes</hi> were got with childe, to bring forth baſtard Poets: without any commiſsion, they do paſſe ouer the Bankes of <hi>Helicon,</hi> till they make the Readers more wearie then Poſt-horſes: while in the meane
<pb facs="tcp:19832:30"/> time, they <hi>Queis meliore luto finxit praecordia Titan,</hi> are better content to ſuppreſſe the out-flowings of their wit, then by publiſhing them, to be accounted Knights of the ſame order. But I that before euer I durſt aſpire vnto the dignitie, am admitted into the companie of the <hi>Paper-blurrers,</hi> do finde the verie true cauſe of our wanting eſtimation, is want of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, taking vppon vs to be <hi>Poets,</hi> in deſpite of <hi>Palla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Now wherein we want deſert, were a thank woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie labour to expreſſe. But if I knew I ſhould haue mended my ſelfe, but as I neuer deſired the title, ſo haue I neglected the meanes to come by it, onely ouer-maſtered by ſome thoughts, I yeelded an inc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie tribute vnto them. Marrie they that delight in <hi>Poeſie</hi> it ſelfe, ſhould ſeek to know what they do, and how they do: and eſpecially looke themſelues in an vnflattering glaſſe of reaſon, if they be enclinable vnto it. For <hi>Poeſie</hi> muſt not be drawne by the eares, it muſt be gently led, or rather it muſt lead, which was partly the cauſe that made the auncient learned affirme, it was a diuine gift &amp; no humane skil; ſince all other knowledges lie readie for anie that haue ſtrength of wit: A <hi>Poet</hi> no induſtrie can make, if his owne <hi>Genius</hi> be not carried into it. And therefore is an old Prouerbe, <hi>Orator fit, Paeta naſcitur.</hi> Yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>confeſſe I alwaies, that as the fertileſt ground muſt be manured, ſo muſt the higheſt flying wit haue a <hi>Dedalus</hi> to guide him. That <hi>Dedalus</hi> they ſay both in this and in other, hath three wrings to beare it ſelfe vp into the aire of due commendation: that is Art, Imitation, and Exerciſe. But theſe neither Artifici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Rules, nor imitatiue paternes, we much comber
<pb facs="tcp:19832:31"/> ourſelues withall. Exerciſe indeed we do, but that verie fore-backwardly; for where we ſhould exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe to know, we exerciſe as hauing knowne: and ſo is our braine deliuered of much matter, which neuer was begotten by knowledge. For there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing two principall parts, Matter to be expreſſed by words, and words to expreſſe the matter: In nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, wee vſe Art or imitation rightly. Our mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is, <hi>Quodlibet,</hi> indeed though wrongly perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, <hi>Ouids</hi> Verſe. <hi>Quicquid conabor dicere, Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus erit:</hi> neuer marſhalling it into anie aſſured ranck, that almoſt the Readers cannot tell where to finde themſelues. <hi>Chawcer</hi> vndoubtedly did excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his <hi>Troilus</hi> and <hi>Creſeid:</hi> of whome trulie I knowe not whether to meruaile more, either that hee in that miſtie time could ſee ſo clearly, or that wee in this cleare age, goe ſo ſtumblingly after him. Yet had hee great wants, fit to be forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen in ſo reuerent an Antiquitie. I account the Mirrour of Magiſtrates, meetly furniſhed of bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful partes. And in the Earle of <hi>Surreis Lirickes,</hi> manie thinges taſting of a Noble birth, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie of a Noble minde. The Sheepheards Kal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender, hath much <hi>Poetrie</hi> in his Egloges, indeed woorthie the reading, if I be not deceiued. That ſame framing of his ſtyle to an olde ruſticke lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, I dare not allow: ſince neither <hi>Theocritus</hi> in Greeke, <hi>Virgill</hi> in Latine, nor <hi>Sanazara</hi> in Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian, did affect it. Beſides theſe, I doo not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to haue ſeene but fewe (to ſpeake bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) printed, that haue poeticall ſinnewes in them. For proofe whereof, let but moſte of the Verſes
<pb facs="tcp:19832:31"/> bee put in proſe, and then aske the meaning, and it will bee founde, that one Verſe did but beget an other, without ordering at the firſt, what ſhould bee at the laſt, which becomes a confuſed maſſe of words, with a tingling ſound of ryme, barely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with reaſons. Our Tragidies and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies, not without cauſe cryed out againſt, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing rules neither of honeſt ciuilitie, nor skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Poetrie.</hi> Excepting <hi>Gorboducke,</hi> (againe I ſay of thoſe that I haue ſeen) which notwithſtanding as it is full of ſtately ſpeeches, and wel ſounding phraſes, clyming to the height of <hi>Seneca</hi> his ſtyle, and as full of notable morallitie, which it dooth moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfully teach, and ſo obtaine the verie ende of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> Yet in truth, it is verie defectious in the circumſtaunces, which greeues mee, becauſe it might not remaine as an exact moddell of all Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidies. For it is faultie both in place and time, the two neceſſarie Companions of all corporall actions. For where the Stage ſhould alway re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent but one place, and the vttermoſte time preſuppoſed in it, ſhould bee both by <hi>Aristotles</hi> precept, and common reaſon, but one day; there is both manie dayes and places, inartificially ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gined. But if it bee ſo in <hi>Gorboducke,</hi> howe much more in all the the reſt, where you ſhall haue <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia</hi> of the one ſide, and <hi>Affricke</hi> of the other, and ſo manie other vnder Kingdomes, that the Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er when he comes in, muſt euer begin with telling where he is, or elſe the tale will not be conceiued. Now you ſhall haue three Ladies walke to gather
<pb facs="tcp:19832:32"/> flowers, and then we muſt beleeue the ſtage to be a garden. By and by we heare newes of ſhipwrack in the ſame place, then we are too blame if we accept it not for a Rock. Vpon the back of that, comes out a hidious monſter with fire and ſmoke, and then the miſerable beholders are bound to take it for a Caue: while in the meane time two Armies flie in, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented with ſoure ſwords &amp; bucklers, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what hard hart wil not receiue it for a pitched field. Now of time, they are much more liberall. For ordinarie it is, that two yoong Princes fall in loue, after many trauerſes ſhe is got with childe, deliuered of a faire boy: he is loſt, groweth a man, falleth in loue, and is readie to get an other childe, and all this in two houres ſpace: which howe abſurd it is in ſence, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſence may imagine: and Arte hath taught, and all auncient examples iuſtified, and at this day the ordinarie players in <hi>Italie</hi> will not erre in. Yet will ſome bring in an example of <hi>Eunuche</hi> in <hi>Terence,</hi> that conteineth matter of two dayes, yet far ſhort of twentie yeares. True it is, and ſo was it to be played in two dayes, and ſo fitted to the time it ſet foorth. And though <hi>Plautus</hi> haue in one place done amiſſe, let vs hit it with him, &amp; not miſſe with him. But they will ſay, how then ſhall we ſet foorth a ſtorie, which contains both many places, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times? And do they not know that a Tragidie is tied to the lawes of <hi>Poeſie</hi> and not of Hiſtorie: not bounde to follow the ſtorie, but hauing libertie ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to faine a quite new matter, or to frame the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie to the moſt Tragicall conueniencie. Againe, many things may be told which cannot be ſhewed:
<pb facs="tcp:19832:32"/> if they know the difference betwixt reporting and repreſenting. As for example, I may ſpeake though I am here, of <hi>Peru,</hi> and in ſpeech digreſſe from that, to the deſcription of <hi>Calecut:</hi> But in action, I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent it without <hi>Pacolets</hi> Horſe. And ſo was the manner the Auncients tooke, by ſome <hi>Nuntius,</hi> to recount things done in former time or other place. Laſtly, if they will repreſent an Hiſtorie, they muſt not (as <hi>Horace</hi> ſaith) beginne <hi>ab ouo,</hi> but they muſt come to the principall poynte of that one action which they will repreſent. By example this will be beſt expreſſed. I haue a ſtorie of yoong <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus,</hi> deliuered for ſafeties ſake with great riches, by his Father <hi>Priamus,</hi> to <hi>Polminester</hi> King of <hi>Thrace,</hi> in the <hi>Troyan</hi> warre time. He after ſome yeares, hearing the ouerthrowe of <hi>Priamus,</hi> for to make the treaſure his owne, murthereth the Childe, the bodie of the Childe is taken vp, <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuba,</hi> ſhee the ſame day, findeth a ſleight to bee reuenged moſte cruelly of the Tyrant. Where nowe would one of our Tragedie writers begin, but with the deliuerie of the Childe? Then ſhould hee ſaile ouer into <hi>Thrace,</hi> and ſo ſpende I know not howe many yeares, and trauaile numbers of places. But where dooth <hi>Euripides?</hi> euen with the finding of the bodie, the reſt leauing to be told by the ſpirite of <hi>Polidorus.</hi> This needes no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee enlarged, the dulleſt witte may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue it. But beſides theſe groſſe abſurdities, howe all their Playes bee neither right Trage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, nor right Comedies, mingling Kinges and Clownes, not becauſe the matter ſo carrieth it, but
<pb facs="tcp:19832:33"/> thruſt in the Clowne by head and ſhoulders to play a part in maieſticall matters, with neither decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie nor diſcretion: ſo as neither the admiration and Commiſeration, nor the right ſportfulneſſe is by their mongrell Tragicomedie obtained. I know <hi>Apuleius</hi> did ſomewhat ſo, but that is a thing recounted with ſpace of time, not repreſented in one moment: and I knowe the Auncients haue one or two examples of Tragicomedies, as <hi>Plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> hath <hi>Amphitrio.</hi> But if we marke them well, wee ſhall finde that they neuer or verie daintily matche horne Pipes and Funeralls. So falleth it out, that hauing indeed no right Comedie in that Comicall part of our Tragidie, wee haue nothing but ſcurrillitie vnwoorthie of anie chaſte eares, or ſome extreame ſhewe of doltiſhneſſe, indeede fit to lift vp a loude laughter and nothing elſe: where the whole tract of a Comedie ſhould be full of delight, as the Tragidie ſhould bee ſtill maintained in a well raiſed admiration. But our Comedients thinke there is no delight without laughter, which is verie wrong, for though laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter may come with delight, yet commeth it not of delight, as though delight ſhould be the cauſe of laughter. But well may one thing breed both togither. Nay rather in themſelues, they haue as it were a kinde of contrarietie: For delight wee ſcarcely doo, but in thinges that haue a conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencie to our ſelues, or to the generall nature: Laughter almoſt euer commeth of thinges moſte diſproportioned to our ſelues, and nature. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb facs="tcp:19832:33"/> hath a ioy in it either permanent or preſent. Laughter hath onely a ſcornfull tickling. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, wee are rauiſhed with delight to ſee a faire woman, and yet are farre from beeing mooued to laughter. Wee laugh at deformed creatures, wherein certainly wee cannot delight. We de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in good chaunces, wee laugh at miſchaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. We delight to heare the happineſſe of our friendes and Countrey, at which hee were wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to be laughed at, that would laugh: we ſhall contrarily laugh ſometimes to finde a matter quite miſtaken, and goe downe the hill againſt the byas, in the mouth of ſome ſuch men as for the reſpect of them, one ſhall be hartily ſorie, he cannot chuſe but laugh, and ſo is rather pained, then delighted with laughter. Yet denie I not, but that they may goe well togither, for as in <hi>Alexanders</hi> pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture well ſet out, wee delight without laughter, and in twentie madde Antiques, wee laugh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delight. So in <hi>Hercules,</hi> painted with his great beard and furious countenaunce, in a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans attyre, ſpinning, at <hi>Omphales</hi> commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it breedes both delight and laughter: for the repreſenting of ſo ſtraunge a power in Loue, procures delight, and the ſcornefulneſſe of the action, ſtirreth laughter. But I ſpeake to this purpoſe, that all the ende of the Comicall part, bee not vppon ſuche ſcornefull matters as ſtirre laughter onelie, but mixe with it, that delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full teaching whiche is the ende of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> And the great faulte euen in that poynt of laughter,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:34"/> and forbidden plainly by <hi>Aristotle,</hi> is, that they ſtirre laughter in ſinfull things, which are rather execra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then ridiculous: or in miſerable, which are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be pitied then ſcorned. For what is it to make folkes gape at a wretched begger, and a beggerly Clowne: or againſt lawe of hoſpitalitie, to leaſt at ſtraungers, becauſe they ſpeake not Engliſh ſo well as we do? What doo we learne, ſince it is certaine, <hi>Nil habet infoelix paupertas durius in ſe, Quam quod ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculos homines facit.</hi> But rather a buſie louing Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier, and a hartleſſe threatning <hi>Thraſo;</hi> a ſelfe-wiſe ſeeming Schoolemaiſter, a wry transformed Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueller: theſe if we ſaw walke in Stage names, which we plaie naturally, therein were delightfull laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and teaching delightfulneſſe, as in the other the Tragidies of <hi>Buchanan</hi> do iuſtly bring foorth a a diuine admiration. But I haue lauiſhed out too many words of this Play-matter; I do it, becauſe as they are excelling parts of <hi>Poeſie,</hi> ſo is there none ſo much vſed in England, and none can be more pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abuſed: which like an vnmannerly daughter, ſhewing a bad education, cauſeth her mother <hi>Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> honeſtie to be called in queſtion. Other ſort of <hi>Poetrie,</hi> almoſt haue we none, but that <hi>Lyricall</hi> kind of Songs and Sonets; which Lord, if he gaue vs ſo good mindes, how well it might be employed, and with how heauenly fruites, both priuate and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, in ſinging the praiſes of the immortall bewtie, the immortall goodnes of that God, who giueth vs hands to write, and wits to conceiue: of which we might wel want words, but neuer matter, of which we could turne our eyes to nothing, but we ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:19832:34"/> euer haue new budding occaſions. But truly many of ſuch writings as come vnder the banner of vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtable loue, if I were a miſtreſſe, would neuer per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade mee they were in loue: ſo coldly they applie firie ſpeeches, as men that had rather redde louers writings, and ſo caught vp certaine ſwelling Phra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which hang togither like a man that once tolde me the winde was at Northweſt and by South, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he would be ſure to name winds inough, then that in truth they feele thoſe paſsions, which eaſily as I thinke, may be bewraied by that ſame forcible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe or <hi>Euergia,</hi> (as the Greeks call it of the writer). But let this be a ſufficient, though ſhort note, that we miſſe the right vſe of the materiall point of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> Now for the outſide of it, which is words, or (as I may tearme it) <hi>Diction,</hi> it is euen well worſe: ſo is it that hony-flowing Matrone <hi>Eloquence,</hi> apparrelled, or rather diſguiſed, in a Courtiſanlike painted affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. One time with ſo farre ſet words, that many ſeeme monſters, but muſt ſeeme ſtraungers to anie poore Engliſhman: an other time with courſing of a letter, as if they were bound to follow the method of a Dictionary: an other time with figures and flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wers, extreemly winter-ſtarued. But I would this fault were onely peculiar to Verſefiers, and had not as large poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among Proſe-Printers: and which is to be meruailed among many Schollers, &amp; which is to be pitied among ſome Preachers. Truly I could wiſh, if at leaſt I might be ſo bold to wiſh, in a thing beyond the reach of my capacity, the diligent Imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of <hi>Tully</hi> &amp; <hi>Demosthenes,</hi> moſt worthie to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated, did not ſo much keepe <hi>Nizolian</hi> paper bookes,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:35"/> of their figures and phraſes, as by attentiue tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as it were, deuoure them whole, and make them wholly theirs. For now they caſt Suger and ſpice vppon euerie diſh that is ſerued to the table: like thoſe <hi>Indians,</hi> not content to weare eare-rings at the fit and naturall place of the eares, but they will thruſt Iewels through their noſe and lippes, becauſe they will be ſure to be fine. <hi>Tully</hi> when he was to driue out <hi>Catiline,</hi> as it were with a thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt of eloquence, often vſeth the figure of repiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>Viuit &amp; vincit, imo inſenatum, Venit imo, inſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natum venit, &amp;c.</hi> Indeede enflamed, with a well grounded rage, hee would haue his words (as it were) double out of his mouth, and ſo do that ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificially, which we ſee men in choller doo natural<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And we hauing noted the grace of thoſe words, hale them in ſometimes to a familiar Epiſtle, when it were too much choller to be chollericke. How well ſtore of <hi>Similiter Cadenſes,</hi> doth ſound with the grauitie of the Pulpit, I woulde but inuoke <hi>Demosthenes</hi> ſoule to tell: who with a rare dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe vſeth them. Truly they haue made mee thinke of the <hi>Sophister,</hi> that with too much ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie would proue two Egges three, and though he might bee counted a <hi>Sophister,</hi> had none for his labour. So theſe men bringing in ſuch a kinde of eloquence, well may they obtaine an opinion of a ſeeming fineneſſe, but perſwade few, which ſhould be the ende of their fineneſſe. Now for ſimilitudes in certain Printed diſcourſes, I thinke all Herberiſts, all ſtories of beaſts, foules, and fiſhes, are rifled vp, that they may come in multitudes to wait vpon any
<pb facs="tcp:19832:35"/> of our conceits, which certainly is as abſurd a ſurfet to the eares as is poſsible. For the force of a ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude not being to proue any thing to a contrary diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puter, but onely to explaine to a willing hearer, when that is done, the reſt is a moſte tedious prat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, rather ouerſwaying the memorie from the purpoſe whereto they were applied, then anie whit enforming the iudgement alreadie either ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, or by ſimilitudes not to be ſatisfied. For my part, I doo not doubt, when <hi>Antonius</hi> and <hi>Craſſus,</hi> the great forefathers of <hi>Cicero</hi> in eloquence, the one (as <hi>Cicero</hi> teſtifieth of them) pretended not to knowe Art, the other not to ſet by it, (becauſe with a plaine ſenſibleneſſe, they might winne cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit of popular eares, which credit, is the neareſt ſteppe to perſwaſion, which perſwaſion, is the chiefe marke of Oratorie) I do not doubt I ſay, but that they vſed theſe knacks verie ſparingly, which who doth generally vſe, any man may ſee doth dance to his owne muſick, and ſo to be noted by the audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, more careful to ſpeak curiouſly then truly. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly (at leaſt to my opinion vndoubtedly) I haue found in diuers ſmal learned Courtiers, a more ſound ſtile, then in ſome profeſſors of learning, of which I can geſſe no other cauſe, but that the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier following that which by practiſe he findeth fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt to nature, therein (though he know it not) doth according to art, thogh not by art: where the other vſing art to ſhew art and not hide art (as in theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes he ſhuld do) flieth from nature, &amp; indeed abuſeth art. But what? methinks I deſerue to be pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded for ſtraying from <hi>Poetrie,</hi> to <hi>Oratory:</hi> but both haue ſuch
<pb facs="tcp:19832:36"/> an affinitie in the wordiſh conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that I think this digreſsion will make my meaning receiue the fuller vnderſtanding: which is not to take vpon me to teach <hi>Poets</hi> how they ſhould do, but only finding my ſelfe ſicke among the reſt, to ſhew ſome one or two ſpots of the common infection growne among the moſt part of writers; that acknowledging our ſelues ſomewhat awry, wee may bende to the right vſe both of matter and manner. Whereto our lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage giueth vs great occaſion, being indeed capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of any excellent exerciſing of it. I knowe ſome will ſay it is a mingled language: And why not, ſo much the better, taking the beſt of both the other? Another will ſay, it wanteth Grammer. Nay truly it hath that praiſe that it wants not Grammer; for Grammer it might haue, but it needs it not, being ſo eaſie in it ſelfe, and ſo voyd of thoſe comberſome differences of <hi>Caſes, Genders, Moods,</hi> &amp; <hi>Tenſes,</hi> which I thinke was a peece of the Tower of <hi>Babilons</hi> curſe, that a man ſhould be put to ſchoole to learn his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tongue. But for the vttering ſweetly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the conceit of the minde, which is the end of ſpeech, that hath it equally with any other tongue in the world. And is perticularly happy in compoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of two or three wordes togither, neare the Greeke, farre beyond the Latine, which is one of the greateſt bewties can be in a language. Now of verſefying, there are two ſorts, the one auncient, the other moderne. The auncient marked the quantitie of each ſillable, and according to that, framed his verſe: The moderne, obſeruing onely number, with ſome regard of the accent; the chiefe life of it,
<pb facs="tcp:19832:36"/> ſtandeth in that like ſounding of the words, which we call Rime. Whether of theſe be the more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, wold bear many ſpeeches, the ancient no doubt more fit for Muſick, both words and time obſeruing quantitie, and more fit, liuely to expreſſe diuers paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions by the low or loftie ſound of the well-wayed ſillable. The latter likewiſe with his rime ſtriketh a certaine Muſicke to the eare: and in fine, ſince it dooth delight, though by an other way, it obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ſame purpoſe, there being in eitner ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and wanting in neither, maieſtie. Truly the Engliſh before any Vulgare language, I know is fit for both ſorts: for, for the auncient, the <hi>Italian</hi> is ſo full of Vowels, that it muſt euer be combred with <hi>Eliſions.</hi> The <hi>Duch</hi> ſo of the other ſide with Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, that they cannot yeeld the ſweete ſlyding, fit for a Verſe. The <hi>French</hi> in his whole language, hath not one word that hath his accent in the laſt ſillable, ſauing two, called <hi>Antepenultima;</hi> and little more hath the <hi>Spanish,</hi> and therefore verie graceleſly may they vſe <hi>Dactiles.</hi> The Engliſh is ſubiect to none of theſe defects. Now for Rime, though we doo not obſerue quantie, yet wee obſerue the Accent verie preciſely, which other languages either cannot do, or will not do ſo abſolutely. That <hi>Caeſura,</hi> or brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing place in the midſt of the Verſe, neither <hi>Italian</hi> nor <hi>Spanish</hi> haue: the <hi>French</hi> and we, neuer almoſt faile off. Laſtly, euen the verie Rime it ſelfe, the <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian</hi> cannot put it in the laſt ſillable, by the <hi>French</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the <hi>Maſculine</hi> Rime; but ſtill in the next to the laſt, which the <hi>French</hi> call the <hi>Female;</hi> or the next be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that, which the Italian <hi>Sdrucciola:</hi> the example
<pb facs="tcp:19832:37"/> of the former, is <hi>Buono, Suono,</hi> of the <hi>Sdrucciola,</hi> is <hi>Femina, Semina.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> of the other ſide, hath both the Male as <hi>Bon, Son;</hi> and the Female, as <hi>Plaiſe, Taiſe;</hi> but the <hi>Sdrucciola</hi> he hath not: where the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh hath all three, as <hi>Du, Trew, Father, Rather, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Potion,</hi> with much more which might be ſayd, but that alreadie I finde the triflings of this diſcourſe is much too much enlarged. So that ſince the euer-praiſe woorthie <hi>Poeſie</hi> is full of vertue breeding de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfulneſſe, and voyd of no gift that ought to be in the noble name of learning, ſince the blames layd againſt it, are either falſe or feeble, ſince the cauſe why it is not eſteemed in England, is the fault of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et-apes, not <hi>Poets.</hi> Since laſtly our tongue is moſt fit to honour <hi>Poeſie,</hi> and to bee honoured by <hi>Poeſie,</hi> I coniure you all that haue had the euill luck to read this inck-waſting toy of mine, euen in the name of the nine <hi>Muſes,</hi> no more to ſcorne the ſacred miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Poeſie.</hi> No more to laugh at the name of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ets,</hi> as though they were next inheritors to fooles; no more to ieſt at the reuerent title of a Rimer, but to beleeue with <hi>Aristotle,</hi> that they were the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Treaſurers of the Grecians diuinitie; to beleeue with <hi>Bembus,</hi> that they were firſt bringers in of all <hi>Ciuilitie;</hi> to beleeue with <hi>Scalliger</hi> that no <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers</hi> precepts can ſooner make you an honeſt man, then the reading of <hi>Virgil;</hi> to beleeue with <hi>Clauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> the Tranſlator of <hi>Cornutus,</hi> that it pleaſed the heauenly deitie by <hi>Heſiod</hi> and <hi>Homer,</hi> vnder the vaile of Fables to giue vs all knowledge, <hi>Logicke, Rheto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke, Philoſophie,</hi> naturall and morall, and <hi>Quid non?</hi> To beleeue with me, that there are many miſteries
<pb facs="tcp:19832:37"/> contained in <hi>Poetrie,</hi> which of purpoſe were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten darkly, leaſt by prophane wits it ſhould be abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: To beleeue with <hi>Landin,</hi> that they are ſo belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Gods, that whatſoeuer they write, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds of a diuine furie. Laſtly, to beleeue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues when they tell you they will make you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal by their verſes. Thus doing, your name ſhall floriſh in the Printers ſhops. Thus doing you ſhalbe of kin to many a Poeticall Preface. Thus doing, you ſhal be moſt faire, moſt rich, moſt wiſe, moſt all: you ſhall dwel vpon Superlatiues. Thus doing, though you be <hi>Libertino patre natus,</hi> you ſhall ſodeinly grow <hi>Herculea proles. Si quid mea Carmina poſſunt.</hi> Thus do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, your ſoule ſhall be placed with <hi>Dantes Beatrix,</hi> or <hi>Virgils Anchiſes.</hi> But if (fie of ſuch a but) you bee borne ſo neare the dull-making <hi>Cataract</hi> of <hi>Nilus,</hi> that you cannot heare the Planet-like Muſicke of <hi>Poetrie;</hi> if you haue ſo earth-creeping a mind that it cannot lift it ſelfe vp to looke to the skie of <hi>Poetrie,</hi> or rather by a certaine ruſticall diſdaine, wil become ſuch a mome, as to bee a <hi>Momus</hi> of <hi>Poetrie:</hi> then though I will not wiſh vnto you the Aſſes eares of <hi>Midas,</hi> nor to be driuen by a <hi>Poets</hi> verſes as <hi>Bubonax</hi> was, to hang himſelfe, nor to be rimed to death as is ſaid to be done in <hi>Ireland,</hi> yet thus much Curſe I muſt ſend you in the behalfe of all <hi>Poets,</hi> that while you liue, you liue in loue, and neuer get ſauour, for lacking skill of a Sonet, and when you die, your memorie die from the earth for want of an Epitaphe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
